Where are the documents?
I told you. I burned them!
Where?
What idiocy.
It's useless to demand
evidence that doesn't exist!
Where are the documents?
Why are you doing this?
Please proceed to the next stage.
Execute us, or whatever else
you have planned!
This is absurd!
If you keep asking the same questions,
the torture will never--
Wait, I see.
So that's your plan.
You want revenge on us
for approaching your daughter.
This is your only chance
to torment us legally!
But are such personal grudges
proper for a believer?
Quit running your mouth.
Where are the documents?
If you don't answer,
he'll be torn from cheek to cheek.
I... I told you. I burned them.
Sir, isn't this going too far?
No.
Treat him later,
so he'll be able to speak.
Yes, sir.
If the mouth won't do...
Huh?
Then next up is the eyes.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE 14
TONIGHT'S SKY...
Stop this immediately.
Even if you do this,
it won't bring back what I burned.
This isn't faith!
Do I look like I'm here for small talk?
Five more breaths,
and I'll pierce his eye.
- Hold it open.
- Huh?
M-Maybe they really burned them?
Five...
Four...
Right now, I want to see
Venus in its final phase.
Three...
I've been waiting
for such a special instant!
Two...
Now then. May God bless you.
One...
Damn it!
You're right.
Everything I said was a lie.
The materials are preserved.
They're in a stone chest
on a certain mountain slope.
Oh? Then take us there.
Very well.
I'm sorry... Oczy.
I'm grateful to you both
for your cooperation.
Get some rest.
We've finally reached the end.
It looks like you were telling the truth.
I'm glad you're a conventional thinker.
After all, the one who left
this chest behind ten years ago
poisoned himself to death to protect it.
It seems you weren't the type
to go that far.
- What kind...
- Huh?
Just what kind of person was he?
I thought you had no interest
in your predecessors.
Well, he was largely the same
as you and all the other heretics.
He threw his entire life away
for the sake of some ridiculous belief.
But what set him apart
was that he was only 12 years old.
That's absurd!
A 12-year-old?
Surprising, right?
Yes.
Then again, it finally makes sense.
Only a 12-year-old
would dare to move the world.
Evening.
Did they get ahold of the stone chest?
Yes.
Are you angry?
Of course not.
You always said we'd leave nothing behind.
Actually, I'm surprised.
You really did save the documents.
And you tried to protect them.
Yeah, I'm as surprised as you.
Why did you confess everything?
We're going to die anyway.
Who cares about my eyes--
You don't get it.
Do you have any idea how painful that is?
It's time.
Put these on and come out.
It's strange...
I've seen it many times,
but when your own time comes,
it doesn't feel real.
What doesn't?
Death.
They've been strange days,
but they're all coming to an end.
I heard the age
of the one who first owned that chest.
How old do you think he was?
Beats me.
He was 12.
Huh? Twelve?!
But that's impossible.
Yeah.
And that means
the unexpected can happen.
Heliocentrism is not dead yet.
What?
I told you in the barn.
I had a backup plan.
But whether it works or not
depends on luck.
There's no time to explain the details,
but if all goes well,
the writing will be reproduced.
But how?
When could all that writing of yours--
Not mine.
What?
The writing that will survive
is yours.
What?!
- M-Mine?
- Yes.
B-But why?
Have you forgotten?
I had no intention of handing
my work to someone else.
Yeah, but--
And in any case,
my writing
was too voluminous to reproduce.
Your writing has no scholarly value,
but that's why it might spread.
What might spread?
Inspiration.
If that alone survives,
the rest will take care of itself.
But leaving something behind
won't be beneficial to you, right?
You're damn right.
Leaving something behind
in the hands of perfect strangers
is meaningless-- no, worthless to me!
However, mysteriously enough,
there may be a realm
that doesn't deem it useless.
For example...
that thing you call history.
Anyway, let's go.
It's time.
In the name of our Lord,
we condemn thee.
Thou hath betrayed
the teachings of the Church
and sullied thyselves
through heretical research.
About your plan...
Huh?
What do you think the chances are
that it will work?
Infinitesimally low.
That's wonderful.
What?
My life ends with hope intact.
The end of life?
Well,
we are standing at the entrance to hell.
No.
Well, we're at an entrance all right.
But it's...
To the heavens.
Do you really think so?
Yes.
The sight that spreads before us now
doesn't look like the entrance to hell.
Tonight's sky
is definitely...
beautiful.
I guess I can believe in that.
We pray that thee be granted
the sacrament of penance.
Because history needs you.
But even if I die...
this world will continue.
That means I can pass the torch.
What if our world really does move?
I've decided to let you view my records.
However, I have one condition.
You must prove true
what I know to be false.
See it.
Look full.
Okay... Go ahead and burn them.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
Hey, what do you think faith is?
Huh?
Faith... or the Church...
Well, it's scripture, of course.
Or doctrine and things.
Why the sudden question?
Sometimes, I lose sight of the answer.
We spend every day
inflicting pain on others.
Yeah, but they're heretics and witches.
They're evil, right?
Yeah. You're right.
So, why is my heart so heavy?
It's the scholars' job
to think about that.
Our job now is to carry out
what our superiors decide.
Hey, there she is.
Let's get to work.
What can I do for you?
Hello, are you Jolenta?
Yes.
We're apprentices of your father.
Is that so?
I'm embarrassed to say it,
but I don't know much
about my father's work.
What is it that you do?
Th-That's, uh...
We're inquisitors.
What?
Inquisitors?
Yes.
And we were hoping to speak with you.
So, what is this about?
Don't worry. We're not here
to arrest you or anything.
We heard from your father.
Six nights ago,
you had dinner with friends, right?
I believe your father visited you there.
The other two men
have been judged as heretics.
To be precise,
they researched a model of the universe
that defies church doctrine.
Do you happen to remember
hearing anything suspicious like that?
If we happen to be arrested in the future,
pretend you know nothing.
No.
I don't know a thing.
Is that so?
But please try and remember.
You seemed quite acquainted.
Did they ever ask
for your help with something?
No, nothing like that.
Well, that's only natural.
The daughter of an inquisitor
assisting a heretic...
It's too far-fetched.
You two, may I have a moment?
A-Antoni!
Over here.
What is it?
Is that Nowak's daughter in there?
Yes. She had contact
with the two heretics,
so just in case...
But she doesn't appear to know anything,
so we were about to let her go.
Oh?
Then prepare her for torture.
- What?!
Think clearly.
The very fact that a woman
sought to be a scholar
is suspicious enough.
I suspect that she's the leader.
Or rather, the demon
that possesses her is.
The two arrested men
were surely just puppets.
You must get to the truth.
B-But sir,
her father is an inquisitor!
The stricter the home,
the greater the temptation.
We've seen many cases of that.
But--
Oh, right. You're the one.
I heard, you know.
You refused to torture a woman
during your training.
And didn't she turn out to be guilty?
Will you let another villain get away?
Unbelievable.
Do you know how much the Church spends
to train new inquisitors?
You'd better give this some thought.
What impressions do your words
and actions leave with others?
And what effect
will that have on your future?
If you understand, get to work.
Excuse me.
Huh?
What?!
These are fine gloves.
H-Hey!
What is the meaning of this?
We're going to interrogate you.
What? Interrogate?
That's right.
About those two heretics?
I told them already.
I don't know anything!
Everyone says that at first.
If you don't answer honestly,
we'll pull your teeth.
Women like to chatter, right?
It's said you're in league with the devil
and use your tongues to spread ruin.
That's implausible reasoning.
Please take it back.
See what I mean?
Now, get going.
- What?
- But...
Come on, you can't be serious.
Are you two really inquisitors?
Fine. I get it.
There. I took the first step for you.
I'll leave the rest to you.
Kids these days are too spoiled.
P-Please don't!
This is...
We have our orders.
We have to obey.
Why don't we use the thumb screw?
What?
I don't want to see her face.
R-Right.
I agree. I'll go get it.
The tables have finally turned
in my favor.
We'll be rid of him now.
If his daughter is judged a heretic,
Nowak is finished.
It's what he deserves
for currying favor with the Bishop
all this time.
Once Nowak is disgraced,
the Bishop's reputation
will suffer by association.
I'll be a more important figure than ever.
This is our chance
to correct the Church's course.
We can't make a living being passive.
Indeed! We're with you!
Did you bring it?
Sorry, I forgot where it's stored.
Could you get it instead?
Huh? Oh, uh... sure.
You have to run! You'll be killed!
Huh? What?!
H-Hey!
This way! Come on!
Wait, um...
I can't let them kill you!
I'll stay behind
and explain to the others.
I'm sure they'll understand.
Why are you doing this?
What do you think faith is?
Huh?
I believe
it's a way of life.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb