Now then. I'll get straight to the point.
Why did you let her go?
No matter... what the truth is,
you intended to kill her.
A most unthoughtful reply.
I can't stand unthoughtful people,
so I'll let you do some thinking.
When you make a decision
under uncertain circumstances,
you should first imagine
the worst-case scenario.
False accusations are deplorable.
But releasing heretics
out of fear of false accusations
is even more so.
A false accusation
will lead to one innocent death.
But if a heretic gets away, at worst,
it could lead to the death
of all humankind.
Do you understand the situation now?
Our enemies are not
mere lowlife criminals.
The heretic you let go
may be the enemy of humans everywhere.
"Love thy enemy."
I devote myself to those words.
I see.
Idiots like you
often misinterpret that verse.
Brush up on your theology.
Does Nowak know about this?
We haven't contacted him yet.
Then tell him this.
Jolenta was a heretic.
She attempted to escape,
took a hostage,
and wounded others in the process.
We were forced to execute her immediately.
Following that,
we carried out official procedures
and burned her at the stake.
Before spreading the ashes in the river,
show Nowak the body.
Tell him it's hers.
Huh?
But where will you get a body?
There's one right here.
This idiot will burn.
Okay... Go ahead and burn them.
Nowak!
Huh?
Just now, at Gallows Number Eight...
What?
Um...
What is it? Spit it out.
I'd like to go home.
Your daughter was arrested as a heretic.
She tried to escape
and is now being executed.
My condolences.
I've heard she was quite intelligent.
I tried to oppose the decision.
She still had a future.
That's right. I brought these for you.
I asked the others not to burn them.
So you could grieve her.
It's against regulations,
but this is a special case.
To be honest,
I've never had
a good impression of you inquisitors.
But now
I see how courageous you really are.
Please allow me
to pray for her too.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
TEN YEARS EARLIER
EPISODE 15
IS IT... MY TURN?
Father! Welcome back!
I'm home, Jolenta.
Were you studying today too?
Good girl.
Yes...
Hey, what's with the long face?
Huh?
Um, look at this.
I don't know if I did it right, but...
"Thank you for always working hard
for God and all of us."
You wrote this letter for me?
Uh, yes.
Is my handwriting poor?
What a sweet child you are.
I've never seen such beautiful penmanship.
I'd better learn from your diligence.
Huh?
Wow! They're great!
Y-You mean it?
Yeah. They'll arrive next week.
I ordered ones just your size.
Yay!
I asked a first-rate artisan too.
Now your hands
won't get cold when you study.
Thank you, Father!
Those words aren't for me.
Huh?
This is the fate that God has granted you.
So when good things happen,
you must first give thanks to God.
- Got it?
- Yes!
Thank you, Lord, for this blessing.
I'm sorry, Jolenta.
Can't you cheer up?
But... you lied to me.
You said the gloves would be just my size!
These are way too big!
It wasn't a lie or anything.
Something must have
gone wrong with the order.
I'm really sorry.
I'll make up for it somehow.
So, please... it's no one's fault.
I never intended to hurt you.
Then it's God's fault.
What... did you say?
You said so, didn't you?
This is the fate that God has granted me!
That means God is at fault!
Take that back! Right now!
Those words are unforgivable!
F-Forget it.
Go get your head straight!
What have I done?
I didn't need to get so angry.
What’s wrong with me?
Then again, faith...
Teaching her faith is most important.
That may be,
but when a child is crying,
what could be more important
than comforting them?
Uh, Jolenta?
I-I'm sorry!
You work hard for God's sake every day.
It's wrong of me to say
that God is at fault!
Look! If I wear them like this,
they fit fine--
I'm really sorry.
Forgive me for being such a fool.
Well,
I'm off!
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
Who would have thought this would happen?
Yes, it's a first in all my years.
I knew I hadn't seen him lately,
but I would've never imagined
Badeni had been executed as a heretic.
Their battle was right nearby
while we slept, right?
What a frightening turn of events.
Did you ever notice him
acting suspiciously, Father Grabowski?
Yes, I'm curious about that too.
Well, how can I put it?
Everything he did was suspicious,
so it's hard to name an example.
Oh, I guess that's true.
Even his appearance was suspicious.
That eye patch he wore frightened me.
Even so, a heretic from our village?
Who was it that noticed?
I heard they received an anonymous tip.
I see.
Whoever it was, we owe them one.
Now we can sleep soundly at night.
Huh? That reminds me.
Didn't you send in a tip recently,
Father Grabowski?
Oh, uh... yes.
Six months ago, I was heading
to the library in the next town,
and I found a book.
I opened it out of curiosity,
and it was full of codes.
I was suspicious,
so I spent a few months decoding it.
The second half seemed to contain
blasphemous ideas.
Oh, but that was the next town over.
It has nothing to do with Badeni.
I see. So that's all it was?
The reason cited
for Badeni's execution
was simply "blasphemy."
There were no details.
It's an inexplicably simple charge,
but was it related to his research?
And if so, what was he researching?
Furthermore,
if he didn't leave notes
about his research behind,
then both the research
and his personal history would be lost.
If my tip was responsible for that...
What have I...
No, it's not possible.
Even if it was his book,
they surely wouldn't
execute him just for that.
What is this?
A letter?
The sender didn't write their name.
It's a poem by Lucretius!
In that case, have you read
Lucretius's work too?
The poet who praised Epicurus.
Well, yes.
If you've read his works,
I'd be grateful
if you could share even a portion--
I'm afraid I refuse.
D-Don't tell me this is from...
"The poem written here
is what I can remember
of Lucretius's work."
"It's only shorthand fragments,
so it's not precise."
"I apologize."
"In return for the poem,
I have a favor to ask."
If you happen to be visited
by a certain beggar, please receive them.
Huh?
I realize that you're unlikely
to fulfill this request.
There's no benefit for you,
and I'm not held in high esteem.
I have no way to convince you.
And that's why,
despite knowing that
these words hold little sway,
I beg you from the bottom of my heart.
P.S.
This is unrelated to the main request,
and a petty nuisance on top of that,
but if you don't mind,
please educate the beggars somehow.
That is all.
Right now,
I am laying eyes on
the poetry of Lucretius,
a man who lived 1,500 years ago.
I can do so because others
spread and preserved his words in writing.
In that case,
if portions of Badeni's research
survive somewhere now,
should they also be spread and preserved?
No.
They're blasphemy after all.
They ought to disappear!
In fact, it's for the better!
Hey, that man with his hair tied
hasn't come lately.
That's why we can't get any bread.
Yes. God has finally abandoned us.
Actually, I made a promise before.
A promise?
To the man with the strange eye patch.
The blond one?
Yes. He told me something.
If a month goes by
with no contact and no bread,
there's a place I should go.
A place?
If we go there, we might receive bread.
Right.
Good idea. I need bread.
I say yes.
No, wait.
Huh?
It might be a trap.
He's the man who did that to our heads
in return for the bread.
Indeed. Who knows
what that man was thinking?
Yes, it's too dangerous.
We can't trust him. I say no.
But...
The one with his hair tied
was always kind.
Excuse me.
I heard that you came
all the way from the next town.
Can I help you?
So you're the one.
The man with the strange eye patch
said you were the man to ask.
"The strange eye patch"?
I knew it. The letter was from Badeni.
Please come with me.
Wait, uh, that's...
If you happen to be visited
by a certain beggar, please receive them.
Very well. Please lead the way.
A-Aren't we there yet?
It's down these stairs.
Where are we?
The man with the strange eye patch
called us all "books."
What? Books?
Whoa! Hey!
He told me I was page one.
What do you mean?
Tattooed writing...
There are 60 pages in all.
What did he mean by "books"?
When he cut our hair, he also told us
to wear hats until it grew back.
Why?
Is it...
Grabowski,
what do you think is necessary
to change such a world?
Huh?
Truth.
Is it... my turn?
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb