25 YEARS LATER
Hey, you're late.
Forgive me.
The prisoner was not easy to capture.
So this is Schmidt?
Yes.
You men wait outside.
Now then.
I don't believe we've met, Schmidt.
Even so, I know all about
your organization.
The Heretic Liberation Front.
You've raided inquisition chambers
in every region and freed the heretics.
Your actions have become
a major source of worry.
Especially you, Schmidt.
Your squad is rather famous
for carrying out
that disgusting initiation test.
I'm sure you've been criticized
even within your organization.
Yet you don't seem fazed.
Is it your goal to kill God?
Well?
No.
You're the ones who kill God.
If I may be so presumptuous,
allow me to reply, inquisitor.
First,
I believe in God.
Second,
I aim to restore God to a state
unblemished by human ideas.
Third,
that goal requires the weakening
of the Church orthodoxy.
As I'm sure you know,
the authority of the Church's
orthodox wing has been wavering lately.
It's not only me.
The times are crying for change too.
Every word you utter
leaves me nauseous, you heretic.
By heretic, do you mean a member
of the faith who opposes church orthodoxy?
That's where we differ.
After all,
I reject all the church's teachings,
no matter which faction.
Or better put,
I reject all religions equally.
I'd like to see them all disappear.
What a load of nonsense.
What do you call yourself then?
A naturalist, I suppose?
A naturalist?
I worship those things where God resides.
I'm not interested in anything man-made.
That's why I have no need
for your man-made teachings or salvation.
An artificial god is out of the question.
God exists beyond reason
and is found in nature.
So that's what makes you a "naturalist"?
You seem to have blind faith
in your own righteousness.
Do you realize how many people have died
from your misunderstanding?
Misunderstanding?
I disdain that word most of all.
How many have you killed
for interpreting
the Holy Scripture differently?
All with blind faith
in your own righteousness.
That's enough!
You can act defiant,
but you're our prisoner now.
You'll soon curse your own fate!
The very idea of cursing one's fate
comes from a lack of faith, inquisitor.
My god is absolute,
and my fate is determined
by what God deems most appropriate.
Unlike you, I don't pray to God
or hope for an answer.
I will gladly accept my fate,
no matter what it may be.
And that means I'm always at an advantage.
Words won't help you now!
In that case,
it's time to begin the operation.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE 16
IT'S TIME TO BEGIN THE OPERATION
In that case,
it's time to begin the operation.
What?
What are you men doing?
I told you to wait outside!
It's no use.
They're with me.
Guards! There are traitors in our midst!
Y-You've got nowhere to run.
Even if you kill me,
the guards are coming!
We know.
After all, we didn't have time
to take them out beforehand.
Are you okay, sir?!
Phew.
You're outnumbered now.
I see. So this is all you have?
Then let's assess the situation.
There are three of us.
Meanwhile, there are ten of you.
I have three goals.
First,
overpower all of you.
Second,
break into the storeroom beneath your feet
and obtain a certain object.
Third,
escape from here.
However, it'd be a pain
to leave through the main gate,
so we'll create a new exit.
An exit?
Now that I think about it,
it's a very difficult task.
Indeed.
If you understand, then surrender now.
That won't do.
Instead, I propose
an ingenious, sophisticated,
precisely crafted,
and innovative solution.
Have you all heard of explosives?
That must be a no.
I figured foot soldiers like yourselves
had already heard the rumors,
but I guess not.
Even I'm not well-versed in their history,
but it's said they come from the East.
I've heard that weapons
applying their formula
were used in the recent factional wars.
Their preparation involves
mixing three ingredients.
Well, I'll skip the details.
To put it simply,
all three of the challenges we face
can be blown away with this.
Blown away?
There's that smoke again.
Even so, you mixed them well, Frei.
To master a difficult science
like the creation of explosives
is truly impressive.
Thank you.
And you did well to carry
such heavy materials, Lewandowski.
Huh? Is that all I get praise for?
Forgive me.
Now then...
Pardon me.
Let's get ahold of what we came for...
and move the Earth.
Who are they?
These are the heretics we liberated
while you spoke with the inquisitor.
They wish to join the Liberation Front.
I see.
Forgive me.
We usually welcome new recruits
right after liberation,
but my squad has all we need.
Another time...
We knew that!
Oh?
But it's because of you
that we wish to join, Captain Schmidt!
We've heard rumors
about the many heretics you've liberated.
We know how you've risked your life
in the fight for freedom.
Please let us join you!
Oh my, what an honor.
If you're that determined,
we'll give you the initiation test.
The Holy Scripture.
Yes, sir.
Initiation test?
As you know, this book
has been your moral support,
the backbone of your daily life,
and the foundation of society.
There's only one thing I ask of you.
Declare you don't believe in it.
Huh?
What?!
Indeed. I understand your hesitancy.
But we're not asking as a casual request.
You must be ready
to change everything from now on.
I promise you this.
If you join me, you will gain
true order and a true god.
However, you cannot bring along
your man-made order and god.
There are only two choices.
Everything else is luxury.
Say we don't believe
in the Holy Scripture?
Surely you must be joking.
Our dispute is only
with the Church orthodoxy,
not with the Church itself.
That includes the Holy Scripture.
Doesn't the Liberation Front
share those same beliefs?
That's correct.
But I'm different.
Are you disappointed?
It seems only the positive rumors
about me have spread.
Is destruction like this necessary?
You could say that destruction
is all that is necessary.
All impure man-made frameworks
must be thoroughly destroyed,
and we must live modestly
in the natural world that is God's order.
That's what is best
for humans as living things.
B-But then we'd be nothing more
than ignorant animals!
Exactly!
In fact, humans are not
so different from animals.
We don't have the capacity
to handle truth appropriately.
Half-truths lead to misunderstanding,
and misunderstanding leads to tragedy.
I can accept tragedies born from nature,
but unnatural tragedies
caused by humans must not be tolerated.
If you agree with me, then declare it now.
I... I can't do it!
I could never do it!
Well done!
I respect your decision!
However, we may fight
to the death at some point.
Let's both be ready for that.
Farewell.
Captain, this seems to be
what we came for.
Oh, is that so?
So this is the book?
Yes. I had a look inside just now.
It definitely states that the Earth moves.
What about the names Oczy or Badeni?
Oczy?
No, I haven't seen those yet.
I see.
Say, what are we gonna do
with that book anyway?
We'll bring it to the leader.
I can't tell you everything until then.
Where is our leader now?
I can't say until we arrive.
Same as always, huh?
But according to the leader,
this is the Liberation Front's
most important mission.
We must accomplish it.
Look!
I see it!
It's the abandoned village!
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
25 YEARS EARLIER
Is that all of them?
Yes.
There you are, dear.
We're ready.
Let's go.
What were those people doing?
They've misunderstood.
H-Hey!
Brother...
I saw you weren't at home.
What are you doing out here at this hour?
Uncle!
Oh, it's you.
Don't scare me like that.
I'm sorry to say so,
but our village has gone mad.
How could they burn the crosses?
Will you go elsewhere then?
Yes, that's right. Will you join us?
No, I can't.
Sorry, kid.
You're hungry, aren't you?
That goes for me too.
Tell me something, Brother.
Why is it that we're so poor?
Why ask that now?
The nobility fights,
and we peasants dedicate our harvest.
That's the way things are.
I don't have time for chatter!
Yes, I understand that.
The nobility do their part.
But what I don't understand is the clergy.
Remember what we were taught?
"It is easier for a camel
to go through the eye of a needle
than for a rich man to enter heaven."
Be diligent. Be humble.
Live a modest life.
Do so, and you will be saved.
It's because we believe those teachings
that we pay tithes to the Church.
But what about them?
They preach about honorable poverty
and fill their bellies with our tithes.
They pass out drunk at taverns,
and some even use their money
to buy poor children.
Y-You...
Tell me, Brother.
Why do churches need
all those lavish decorations?
Why must the faithful be divided by class?
Why do we have to stay quiet
and accept things as they are?
Y-You're right to point those things out.
But if our village uses
such violent means,
divisions within the Church
will only grow!
At this rate, our village...
All of us will be labeled heretics.
I see. So that's your answer.
It seems we can't agree.
- Dear!
- Run!
Why... don't you get it over with?
I'm giving you time.
Time to understand your own shallowness.
Time to experience despair.
And finally, time to repent.
It's not too late.
Say you were mistaken.
Say that the Church orthodoxy is mistaken!
Say it now!
Save... our child...
He's dead.
Run!
You bitch!
Mother!
Run!
Let go!
According to the leader,
there should be supplies here.
Let's rest and replenish.
Damn it.
Every village we find
is dead from the plague!
It's enough to make you heartsick.
But I guess we can use them
for our missions.
Yeah.
And you're really loud, you know?
Huh? Does that matter now?
No.
Okay, we can use this place.
Frei, continue confirming
the contents of the book.
We'll gather the supplies.
Yes, sir.
Huh?
According to the map, it should be...
Someone's here.
Man... What a weird book.
What exactly was it written for?
And what does the leader want with it?
Who are you? What are you doing here?
I'm resting.
You're here to pillage the ruins.
Come with me.
I'll hand you over to the Bishop.
Fine. Let's go.
Please calm yourself.
Where did you come from?
What's your name?
That's...
Forgive me, Captain.
Where's the book?
I hid it in a drawer in that house.
Let's get it and leave.
It seems the Church's minions are here.
Hey! Who's there?
Damn it. What do we do now?
The book is safely hidden.
I believe the wise choice
is to regroup and collect it later.
Let's do that.
Halt!
W-We let the intruders escape,
Bishop Antoni...
It's fine. They're not important.
Let them be.
I think this one offers us a lot more.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb