The truth is
I'm an inquisitor.
Is that so?
I guess that would be
a hard thing to tell your daughter.
Oh, my!
So you understand?
That's exactly right.
I'm proud of what I do,
but the details are what they are,
so I just keep putting it off.
Setting that aside,
we recently received a letter
that contained a certain tip.
The writer of the letter
came across a diary full of codes
on their visit to town.
Thinking it was suspicious,
they decoded it using frequency analysis,
and it turned out that the diary
dealt mostly with advanced astronomy.
However, in its latter pages,
the diary suddenly began to propose
an abnormal model of the cosmos.
My superiors felt that
the tip was reliable,
and they dispatched me.
But unluckily for me,
the sender didn't identify themselves.
When that happens,
I have to gather the breadcrumbs myself.
I'll get to the point.
I know it's sudden,
but would you be willing
to show me your research?
Don't worry.
I don't suspect you of anything.
You're friends with my daughter after all.
Even so, my orders call for me
to investigate any researchers I find.
Uh, well, that's...
Of course, I don't mind.
Then please lead the way.
This is my study.
I see.
Then if you don't mind...
Huh?
This is...
It certainly is cluttered in here.
I apologize.
Not at all.
I'm the one making the sudden intrusion.
By the way, what do you research mainly?
Astrology.
I'm looking into
the misfortunes that occur
when Mars is in opposition to the Sun.
I see.
Hey, that's--
Well?
Yes. This is acceptable.
Right.
All clear.
No problems here, either.
Well then.
I'm sorry for taking up your time.
Everything looks fine.
Yes. Naturally.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE 12
HELIOCENTRISM IS MY FAITH
Dear me, it's all so harmless.
I apologize for suspecting you.
I feel rather silly now.
Did I offend you?
No. It's fine.
I really do apologize.
Thanks for your cooperation.
Farewell.
I thought we were done for.
We'd better speed up our plans.
I'll leave here tomorrow or the day after.
You should too.
R-Right.
Luck was on our side today.
I may have hidden the documents,
but I didn't expect him
to leave so easily.
Yeah.
He didn't seem to notice
the necklace either.
- The necklace?
- Huh?
You know, that one.
What about this?
Uh, didn't I tell you?
Well...
In my previous job,
I took part in a heretic transfer.
That necklace belonged to the heretic.
The inquisitor who accompanied us
was that man, Nowak.
A lot happened,
and I ended up fleeing to this village.
But just before my escape,
the heretic gave me that.
Still, Nowak didn't react,
so he must have forgotten.
With all the chaos,
he may not have seen me take it.
Get ready within the next hour.
Huh?
We're leaving immediately.
It's probably okay, but just in case,
we should assume the worst.
I'm sorry.
Forget the apologies. Just get ready.
I've finished getting ready.
Good.
Take the tunnel and head for the stable.
There, steal a horse
and head to your destination.
What are you going to do, Badeni?
Once the documents are fully burned,
I'll write a letter and then leave.
Then that means
we won't see each other for a while.
Indeed.
Let's meet again as the world turns.
Are you going to burn everything?
Yes.
I'll take what I need most,
but it's dangerous to leave the rest.
But even if it were safe,
I wouldn't leave anything.
As I said before,
this work must be mine alone.
I won't hand over my materials to anyone.
What is it?
Do you have a complaint now?
N-No, I would never...
Actually,
I do.
Um, if you keep isolating yourself,
won't it be harder to notice mistakes?
And isn't that harmful to research?
Oh, I know it's not my place!
I don't understand academic matters.
I'm merely rambling. Just forget--
I'm listening.
Count Piast
was dissatisfied with the errors
and complications of the current model,
so he tried to discover a new one, right?
Not only that,
he made one that was highly accurate.
That is, compared
to other geocentric models.
So what separates us
from Count Piast?
You can challenge
mathematical errors on paper.
But without firm proof,
in the end,
no one can claim with certainty
that heliocentrism is the truth.
In that case,
the difference
between us and him isn't much.
Even so,
he believed in the possibility
that he was wrong and accepted the truth.
Are you trying to say
that heliocentrism is wrong?
N-No! That's not what I mean.
All I'm trying to say is...
Isn't it important to acknowledge
that you might be wrong?
Especially when it comes to stuff
like scholarship and research.
If you don't allow others
to dispute your ideas,
it's more like...
faith.
The sanctity of faith
goes beyond logic or reason,
but shouldn't it be kept separate
from research?
That's why it's important to have
other people who can offer criticism.
You shouldn't shut them out.
What made you...
What made you think that?
Long ago,
I learned that such a thing is hope.
Huh?
My former work mentor
and the heretic who gave me the necklace...
After they encountered the stone chest,
they both found hope
in passing the torch to others.
And to my surprise,
that was more important to them
than going to heaven.
It puzzled me for the longest time.
Passing the torch or trusting others
might sound nice in theory,
but you'll never know
if the other person will really carry on.
Worse than that,
they might reject your plans in the end.
In that sense, entrusting things to others
is scary, not hopeful.
But in fact,
maybe having others refute
or correct your ideas
is what passing the torch really means.
Things don't go as planned.
Misunderstandings
or unexpected events occur.
The believer is opposed by the heretic.
Heliocentrism is opposed by
the geocentric model.
The twists brought on
by those outside elements
might be the very thing
that gives you hope
to move forward.
Oh, but when it comes to heliocentrism,
it's too dangerous
to tell others, of course.
I see what you mean.
However, I don't agree.
What you're saying
is incredibly dangerous.
As I said, I'm only speaking
about your stance toward research.
When it comes to faith--
It's the stance that is dangerous.
Applying that stance to research
would mean abandoning the absolute truth,
which should always be our goal.
Scholars would swim forever
in the waters of imperfection.
You're asking us to accept
such a tragedy with open arms?
Yes.
Isn't that better
than forever believing in a mistake?
We'll debate that thought at a later date.
It's pointless to stay here any longer.
Okay.
Well then. Until we meet again.
Right.
Thank you for all you've done for me.
What is it?
Aren't you going?
- They're coming.
- Huh?
A carriage is coming.
It's the inquisitors' carriage.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
How long before they reach here?
Um... probably four or five minutes.
Damn it!
Throw that in the fire!
Then hit the tunnel and run!
But...
I'll follow when I gather my things.
Uh, right!
Didn't you say
you were going to write a letter?
Huh? There's no time for that!
Can we have a little chat?
Uh, yes.
I'm not trying to push
my personal concerns onto you,
but this particular case is special to me.
It's because
the heretics we're pursuing
have approached my family.
So, at the moment,
I'm in a peculiar mood.
To put it simply...
I'm pissed off.
Was that letter something important?
Of course it was!
I had a plan!
But there's no use now.
Besides, just writing it is pointless!
As of yesterday, I could have sent it.
But after today, all letters to the church
will be intercepted.
Even if I managed to write it,
I'd have to take it to the church
via the tunnel.
There's no time for that!
I don't even have time
to explain this to you!
Even if you give up on that,
we only have five minutes.
What?
How long would you need to flee safely?
It's meaningless to speculate!
How many minutes do you need?
Around ten minutes.
Hey.
Do you intend to die?
I don't know.
But I do know that I can buy time.
Are you that stupid?
You'd be drawing your sword on clergymen.
At this rate,
they're likely to capture us both.
If that's the case,
at least one of us should get away.
I don't think you understand.
You'd almost certainly
be condemning yourself to hell.
Why should you condemn your soul
for the sake of this research?
Before, you asked me
why I decided to write a book.
Huh?
It's probably because
when I learned
the meaning of heliocentrism,
it inspired me.
That inspiration has grown day by day.
What are you trying to say?
I'm saying that
there was a time not long ago
when I was desperate to leave for heaven.
But now, if it will protect
that inspiration,
I'm ready for hell.
This is what it means...
to learn something, I think.
You're making a mistake.
Am I?
Yes. You are.
It's people like you
who have never studied theology
and are ignorant of hell
that tend to make bad choices.
Even if that's true,
I won't regret it.
Have you forgotten
the speech you gave me earlier?
You said it was important
to accept criticism from others.
To involve yourself in such a way
with a scholarly theory like heliocentrism
is a grave mistake.
Yes. You're right.
But even so...
Heliocentrism is my faith.
Wait.
Lord God,
our savior has promised us.
"I am the resurrection and the life:
he that believeth on me,
though he die, yet shall he live."
O merciful God,
take this man whom you have called
from life to yourself.
Welcome him safely
to the promised kingdom.
Absolve him of every bond of sin,
and let him live among those
you have chosen in eternal light.
May he be raised in the glory
of the resurrection.
In the name of our Lord.
Amen.
Whoa!
Oh?
Well, well...
I wasn't expecting a welcome party.
Ready your fire.
Give yourself up!
Why do all this
just for that stupid theory?
Because I want to have hope
for this world.
I won't surrender, but couldn't we talk?
Fire at will.
By the way, do you have battle experience?
It's my first time.
This is the best I get, huh?
What?
Forget it. It's nothing.
Sir, I am here to fulfill my duty.
Yeah, I suppose.
But fulfilling your duty
comes down to individual will.
The will to put your life in danger.
Are you ready for that?
Yes, sir!
Years ago, my sibling
was killed by a madman.
The investigation concluded that
the killer was possessed by the devil.
I wouldn't say I harbor a grudge,
but I'm prepared to kill heretics.
That's good to hear.
But it's not quite what I meant.
I was once a mercenary.
You might look down on such bloody work,
but it taught me many things.
A truly strong warrior
is not one who's ready to kill.
It's one who is ready to die.
In battle, crude determination
is superior to superficial skill.
So what I'm really asking
is if you're prepared to die
for your murdered sibling's sake.
Yes!
Seriously?
Come on...
This is why new recruits are useless.
You're not prepared to die, are you?
We're about to find out.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb