EPISODE 18
TO LIBERATE INFORMATION
You're a Church authority, aren't you?
Should you really be doing this?
A nomad like you has no room to talk.
Show some respect.
Our Church was more than happy
to welcome you itinerants as converts.
We gave you civilization.
Hmm?
You people are all the same.
You think you are rational and superior,
while others are primitive and inferior.
You say you'll guide others
down the right path,
but you actually continue excluding them.
My people converted
several generations ago,
but we still face discrimination.
Doesn't that go against
the teachings of the Holy Scripture?
It's no wonder
divisions within the Church are growing.
- Oh?
- Hold it!
Don't talk to the Bishop like that!
This man told us something.
He said you have a shred of intelligence.
You instructed people to collect fabrics
from the abandoned villages, right?
Why fabrics?
Most people would aim
for something more valuable.
Finding valuables takes time,
and there's obviously more competition.
But most importantly,
money alone is not the key to earning.
If all we have is money, it only depletes.
That's why looking for money itself
isn't a good strategy.
To really earn money,
what we need is to produce.
That's where fabrics come in.
They can easily be turned into
clothes, dressings, or even pouches.
In other words, easily made products!
Um, Bishop--
I see. Then tell me this.
What do you think will happen
to Church authority in the future?
W-What are you--
Answer me.
I think it will waver.
How do we stop that?
You can't.
So if you want to maintain your wealth,
you'd better act soon.
That means correctly assessing the future.
And you can do that?
Who knows?
But if I can't, I'll merely die.
Come to the church immediately.
I want to talk more.
Huh? Wait...
Um, what about me?
Do as you please.
Draka, I've always believed in you.
I knew you'd find a way out of--
Stop talking.
Which church are we going to?
We'll descend to the southwest, and--
Oh, that town?
By the way, what is that book?
Oh, this is...
What do I do?
This heliocentrism thing
goes against the church's teachings.
Hand it over.
But maybe this Bishop...
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
W-We're under attack!
What are you doing? Defend me!
Retreat!
Hey, they're getting away!
Let them go, Lewandowski.
It's time for us to go too.
Still, isn't it too much of a coincidence?
Running into church officials again...
Yeah, talk about rotten luck.
That's exactly why it feels like fate.
Where could God be leading us this time?
- Uncle?
- D-Draka...
H-Help me...
You were ready to sell me out just now.
The audacity you have.
Is this what you wanted, Uncle?
Your conviction
is about to lead you to hell.
I told you.
There is... no hell.
Damn... it.
- You.
- Huh?
Who... are you people?
The better question is who are you?
Why do you have that book?
I found it by chance in that house.
I see.
It belongs to us.
Give it back.
What exactly is this book?
All I can say is that
it's not meant for you.
Hand it over.
My uncle is dead because of you people.
Don't you owe me more of an explanation?
I apologize for that.
That book is important.
That's the explanation. Hand it over.
Important? Important how?
We didn't come here to chat.
We came to reclaim the book.
You merely found it by chance.
This has nothing to do with you.
Consider that my final warning.
Hand it over. I don't want to use force.
Could it be that I'm destined
to live my whole life here, as I am?
One day, that conviction
will show you the way.
With that, you'll have the courage
to stand your ground.
If I let this moment pass... I'll never...
You people came here today
to reclaim this book.
I have nothing to do with it.
Even so, you'll have to forgive me...
because I came here tonight
to change my fate.
W-What are you doing?!
I know the contents.
Maybe not perfectly,
but I have a good memory.
Who'd believe that?!
You have no choice.
Frei.
Do you remember the contents?
If you do, I'll dispose of this girl.
No, I never finished reading it.
As for the contents...
I was careless.
It's fine. I'm at fault
for allowing it to be burnt.
I'm sorry, everyone.
We'll have to take her to the leader.
Are you sure?
There's no other way.
It's fate.
Come with us!
Th-Thank you.
So long, Uncle.
Well, Frei?
She really does seem to remember.
Although I can only confirm
the half that I read.
How about it?
Do you trust me a little now?
I'm Draka. Pleased to meet you.
I'm Lewandowski.
I'm Frei.
And I'm their Captain, Schmidt.
We're members
of the Heretic Liberation Front.
That was a poor way to meet,
but if you're coming with us,
there's no need to fight.
Let us deepen
our understanding of one another
and cooperate to achieve our mutual goals.
I hope work can proceed smoothly.
In other words,
what we need now is dialogue.
Right.
He's so long-winded.
So first, why did you burn the book?
What motivated you
to want to come with us so badly?
I sensed I could make money
if I'm involved with that book.
Earning money is my conviction.
Conviction?
I hold convictions myself,
so I can sympathize.
Although mine are loftier.
However, I'd like you to prepare.
Everything you are about to see
will be painful for one who believes
in the Church orthodoxy.
I don't mind that.
I'm not one of the faithful.
Huh?
I'm not interested
in interpreting the Holy Scripture.
Oh my, you too?!
That makes things easier.
We feel the same way.
Y-You do?!
Then do you also think
the Church's class system is ridiculous?
Yes! Of course.
And you don't believe this world
was created for humanity's sake?
Of course not!
Then you don't believe in God either.
Huh?
What does that mean?
Is your heresy against something
other than Church orthodoxy?
No, I don't believe in God.
What?
So you believe in another religion?
No, I don't believe in God.
So, in other words...
You don't believe in God?
That's what I just said.
- Um...
- Wait!
I need a moment.
I see!
So this is fate too.
First off, I've never met anyone
who held such a belief.
To be honest, I'm quite unsettled
to the point of rage.
But at the same time,
I realize now that this is the fate
God has assigned me.
I will accept that.
But when our involvement is over,
I hope that your fate
is to vanish as soon as possible.
Uh, right.
He's so long-winded.
I guess that means
you all have a firm belief in God.
It's no mere belief.
There is a God.
The proof is that the world exists.
So there must be a maker.
However, God has no personality,
nor can they be interpreted.
All I do
is worship the natural world God created.
Hold on.
Isn't worshiping nature itself
a kind of interpretation?
No, that is incorrect.
The reason is that
I'm simply doing what I enjoy.
It comes from feeling, not logic.
It's not an interpretation.
By the same token, I despise religion
not because it is illogical,
but because it is logical.
God's motives could never
be understood by humans.
God made the vast natural world,
but it's not for the sake of humankind.
God defines my fate,
but I don't know where I'll be led.
Uh...
Well, I'll put it simply.
I place no trust
in the intellect of people
who attempt to understand.
Then I'm afraid I can't agree.
After all,
people use their intellect
and logic for progress.
If we abandon that,
how will society evolve?
The concepts of progress or evolution
are unnatural in and of themselves.
Make what you need,
when and where you need it.
Isn't that enough?
The unnatural desire
for comfort leads to conflict
and a chaotic world.
Oh?
Even so, I think some lives
are saved by technology.
Should lives that were destined to end
be saved by unnatural means?
No human life should take priority
over what God has determined.
That's ridiculous!
It would make us God's slaves!
Well, I'd prefer that
to human pride and conceit.
Is that so?
I don't think you're the least bit right.
I can say the same for you.
It seems further dialogue is meaningless.
How about this? At times like these...
Heads, I'm right.
Tails, you're right.
Look at that. It's heads.
It seems I'm right this time.
What's your point?
I never agreed to accept the result.
In the first place,
I don't leave such things to chance.
Well, you'll understand one day.
Hmm?
It's time.
Stop the carriage.
Yes, sir!
Huh? What's going on?
It's the start of a new day.
Um, what are you doing?
I'm bathing in the morning sun.
When I do that, I feel it.
Feel what?
God.
You got out just for this?
I was born just for this.
I don't get it.
Why don't you come out?
Do you feel nothing
in the presence of this majestic dawn?
I do feel something.
Agony.
What?
Dawn illuminates everything,
whether you like it or not.
Even when you want to hide
or turn your eyes away,
it still comes.
And there's never a day
when the sun doesn't rise.
No one can run from it.
It reminds me of "fate,"
that word I despise.
The morning sun disgusts me.
Even if I die, I'll never understand
what's so great about it.
Is that so?
- Then go ahead and die.
- Huh?!
I just said, "Even if I die"!
Don't give up so easily.
You never know until you try.
Anyway, if we're done debating,
will you answer my question?
What do you intend to do with that book?
We'll arrive soon.
Isn't it about time you told us
what our mission is too?
Yes, you're right.
Are you all aware
of the three inventions that are poised
to shake up the world?
The first is explosives.
The second is the compass.
And then there's the third,
which concerns us the most.
Movable type!
Movable type?
Yes.
The traditional methods of copying books
are handwritten manuscripts
or making woodblock prints of each page.
However, movable type is different.
The procedure is simple.
First, you make molds
called type for each letter.
Next, you line them up
and make a letterpress.
Then, you cover them with ink
and apply the letterpress to paper.
Through that process alone...
Through that alone--
You can mass-produce manuscripts
with astonishing speed
and uniform quality.
What an idea... It's incredible.
The book's content,
the times, and technology
are all in place.
Then that means your objective...
Yes.
Our objective
is to publish that book.
It's a mission of the highest priority
passed down directly by our leader.
And so, Draka...
We need your memory of the book's contents
to remain firm.
Still, what does the leader want
from that book?
The leader believes
that spreading the book's ideas
will deal a blow to the values
of the Church orthodoxy.
In the leader's words,
"The absolute will be no longer."
Will it really be that simple?
Who knows?
But the potential rewards are huge.
What is it?
If you have doubts, don't hold back.
Very well.
Our task is to carry out liberation.
Isn't this outside of our scope?
I'll answer like this.
One could call this
the most important liberation of all.
In other words,
we're going to liberate information.
At present, we live in a world
where information is imprisoned.
That includes censorship
of books by authorities
and mutual collective surveillance.
In the end, we look for cues out of fear
and avoid speaking out.
Freedom of information
will lead to a freer society.
Long ago, at the Academy,
Plato and Aristotle lived together,
despite their differing ideas.
It's only when diverse opinions
gather in the open
that reason is perfected.
Or so the leader thinks.
That's why it's important for us
to shoulder the publication,
release the information,
and free the people.
And once the book is published,
we will use the Reformation
to distribute it.
That Reformation?
Yes.
The same Reformation that recently fought
a fierce war with the orthodoxy.
But they emphasize
the Holy Scripture most of all.
Will they accept heliocentrism?
The leader has a plan for that too.
Plus, many of them
separate faith from reason.
They are not a monolithic group.
Hey!
The conversation will have to pause!
We've arrived.
Long time no see.
Oh, what an honor.
We're grateful you came to greet us.
Draka, allow me to introduce you.
This is the leader
of the Heretic Liberation Front...
Jolenta.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb