To obtain bread, one offers coin.
To obtain rights, one offers taxes.
To obtain wages, one offers labor.
So then,
what must one offer up
to obtain the truth of our world?
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EARLY 15TH CENTURY
SOMEWHERE IN THE KINGDOM OF P
Three for Wojcik.
Two for Mazur.
For Bolanski...
Four.
I only realized it
after assuming this line of work,
but do you know
what troubles people the most
when their nails are removed?
They... They can't hold objects.
Without nails, we have no grip.
Oh, my!
An answer befitting a scholar.
However, it's incorrect.
The answer is pain.
It's the simplest things
that seem to trouble people the most.
Now then,
you've hidden research materials
that blaspheme against Church doctrine.
Where are they?
Where?
Where are the materials?
You...
You bastards have no power over the truth!
Oh, dear.
Are you by chance a strong-willed fellow?
What a bother.
This could take a while.
I'd like to go home early.
I only have ten nails.
Just get it over with!
For Negri... 68.
What?
Nails grow back, you know.
Okay, everyone. I have a question.
What lies at the center of the universe?
Sir! I know!
Oh!
Go on, Kochanski.
It's love!
The center of the universe
overflows with God's love.
That is correct.
But it's a little too abstract.
Anyone else... Oh!
Rafal, go ahead!
Yes, sir.
The center of the universe
is the Earth, of course.
We know this for many reasons.
As Aristotle pointed out,
heavy objects fall downward.
Objects fall to the ground
because the Earth is the lowest sphere
in the center of the universe.
Exactly!
You honor me, my son.
The honor is mine, Professor Potocki.
Come on, are you two bragging?
No, not at all.
The bragging begins now.
Big news! Rafal is going to university!
- What?!
These days, only a handful of people
can enter university,
but to do so at age 12 is truly amazing.
It calls for celebration!
- Wow!
- That's awesome!
Rafal, have you thought
of an appropriate field of study?
Mathematics?
Medicine?
Geography?
Of course, I want to study theology.
As we all know,
theology is the highest academic field.
We owe our lives to God.
A theologist analyzes
the holy scripture logically
so that we may deepen our faith.
I don't believe I have
more talent than anyone else.
I am merely lucky.
That's why I want
to repay that good fortune
by choosing a field
that will be useful to the faithful.
Magnificent!
You are an example to us all!
Oh, stop.
This world
is so easy!
Though it pains me to say it,
the world is full of fools.
I myself was born an orphan,
so I've had my share of poverty,
misery, pity, vulnerability,
and every other disadvantage.
But above all that,
I'm good at living smart.
Really good.
My philosophy
is to live rationally.
If one ignores
irrational emotions like love,
avoids wasteful desires,
and makes reasonable decisions,
one can live comfortably.
That which is rational
is always beautiful.
By sticking to that belief,
people now see me as dignified,
wise, humble, and capable.
University? That's awesome, Rafal!
I can brag about knowing you!
No, I'm nothing special.
Simpletons like this guy Kochanski
respect me right away,
so they're good to have around.
You're a genius.
Not at all.
A sage.
You're exaggerating.
No, more like a god!
Uh-oh.
God?
What are you saying?
Humans cannot be gods.
Please retract that comment.
I take it back.
Forgive me.
Be careful from now on.
You idiot.
Some things can't be said aloud.
That concludes today's lesson.
May God bless you.
Oh, Rafal.
- I have a favor to ask.
- Oh?
What is it?
I need you to-- Huh?
Is that a catalog of stars?
Uh, yes!
Yesterday, I saw my first
sixth-magnitude star.
It was so exciting!
I see.
Then you must stop.
What?
You must devote all your time
to theology from now on.
No more astronomy.
Understood?
Y-Yes sir.
Good.
As for the favor,
I'd like you to pick up
my acquaintance Hubert tomorrow.
Hubert?
Wasn't he arrested as a heretic?
Something about forbidden research.
Is it okay to take him in?
Yes. It's fine.
He recanted, so they're releasing him.
Willingness to forgive sins
is a sign of devout faith.
I'll be loaning him
a place to live as well.
Now then. I'm counting on you.
You must devote all your time
to theology from now on.
No more astronomy.
It's only natural.
I've got no time for astronomy.
Stop it.
You've got to forget about the sky.
What does it matter?
There was a time
when I saw a rational beauty
in the orderly movements of stars.
But when I looked deeper,
every star's movement
has its own complex calculations.
Continuing with astronomy isn't rational.
Plus,
the world of stars is so far away.
No matter how we stretch,
no human can ever reach them.
Hubert...
A former scholar and heretic.
What kind of person could he be?
No matter how you look at it,
it's not a smart way to live.
Speak of the devil.
A heretic was scheduled
for execution today.
Come on, they defied God!
Surely there were chances to recant.
They brought it on themselves.
Hurry up and burn already.
What's taking so long?
What's with that guy?
Let's get out of here.
Excuse me!
I'm Rafal, ward of Potocki.
I'm here for Hubert.
Oh, uh...
Right.
Whoa! He's huge!
This guy is suspicious to the core!
Pleasure to meet you.
I'm Potocki's ward, Rafal.
I look forward to knowing you.
Huh?
Uh, um...
I offer no benefit to you.
You don't have to win
my favor with a false smile.
What?
But...
Now then. Please guide me.
I've heard about you.
You're going to university?
Uh, yes! It's an honor.
I owe it to God
and everyone who has supported--
Will you study astronomy?
What?
You must look at stars
if you carry an astrolabe.
Oh, uh... This is...
How do I put it? It's just a hobby.
I've been thinking of quitting.
I'm going to study theology--
You're rather insincere.
Huh?
So, Hubert, what were you
researching before?
Is that wax tablet
a record of your observations?
Yes.
To the best of my ability, I--
- Show me.
- Whoa! Hey...
Excellent.
What?
You've seen all the way
to the sixth magnitude.
You have good eyes.
What?
Oh, but those are just jottings.
I have more precise notes at home.
You do? I'd like to see them.
I can continue my research with these.
Right!
Of course, I--
Huh?
Did you say... research?
You abandoned your research, didn't you?
I'm a scholar.
No matter what anyone says,
I will never abandon my research.
Huh? Does that mean you haven't recanted?
Of course not.
I lied to obtain my release.
Although, I will keep up the act
to avoid being caught.
Wha--
Why did you reveal that so bluntly?
Because I'm about to blackmail you.
What?!
Listen to me.
Research requires observation.
However, my eyes have weakened.
That's why I'll use yours.
A heretic caught twice
is immediately executed.
I'm out of chances.
I came back to finish what I started.
And I'll jump through fire to do it.
My apologies,
but if you refuse, I'll kill you.
If you interfere, I'll kill you.
If you don't do what I say
at all times, I'll kill you.
So continue astronomy!
For my sake.
That's an order.
Understood?
Y-Yes! I'll do it!
I'll do anything you say!
Don't worry.
I'm not an unreasonable man.
I-I'm glad to hear you say that.
Where do you usually observe?
A hill to the southeast.
I know a better spot.
You're in for a surprise.
I'll tell you tomorrow.
R-Right.
Well, I'll be going.
What the heck?!
Why the heck did they let that creep out?
He should be burned alive!
I'll turn him in right away.
Does he really think I'll go tomorrow?!
I know a better spot.
You're in for a surprise.
Come on. This is way too dangerous.
There's no way I'll go.
Nothing good will come of it!
Wow... Amazing!
I'm so glad I came!
I never knew they could be so clear!
Indeed.
The altitude is high,
the field of view is broad,
and the air is clear.
It's perfect for observation.
Not only that...
I'm fond of the way those mountains
and rocks resemble Orion's Belt.
Oh... right.
Observation is difficult
once the moon is out.
I'll calculate the time retroactively,
so make your record now.
Right.
Is this good enough?
Incredible.
This many in such a short time.
Oh, uh... thanks.
- Excuse me.
- Hmm?
What exactly will you
use these records for?
This forbidden research of yours...
What is it?
Have you heard of Aristarchus?
Huh? What is that?
In that case, do you know the shape
of the cosmos?
Huh?
Yes.
Earth is at the center,
and all the heavenly bodies
perform complex revolutions around it.
- Draw it for me then.
- What?
Something like this, I think.
It's hard to understand,
but Ptolemy discovered the truth
over 1,000 years ago.
Plus, common sense
tells us that the Earth is special.
I believe God
would place it at the center.
Indeed.
In that case,
is there beauty in such truth?
What?
Is the universe you described beautiful?
Whether it's beautiful or not
depends on the sense of the individual.
It has nothing to do with scholarly truth.
You didn't answer the question.
Do you find it to be beautiful?
Well, it does seem
a little too complicated.
With this model, every planet
has to be calculated separately.
The way the movements fail to form
a single orderly system...
doesn't seem rational.
In that sense,
it's not very beautiful.
But while the lack
of beauty is unfortunate,
there could never be one system
that accounted for the entire universe.
It makes no sense
to fault the universe for that.
No, it's a major fault.
What?
I don't want to live
in a universe that isn't beautiful.
Even if that's the case,
to place beauty before logic
is just plain backwards.
It may be complicated,
but the theory is highly accurate.
As long as the stars move
and the sun rises, that is.
And what if neither the sun
nor the stars actually move?
Come on, a theory like that
would never hold up.
But it does.
If that's true, then what's moving
in the universe as we speak?
The Earth.
The Earth? But that's--
Wait... The Earth?
That's right.
The sun does not rise. We descend.
Morning comes every day
because the Earth rotates
on its own axis.
In addition, the seasons change
because the Earth moves
in an orbital revolution around the sun.
In my universe,
the Earth moves in two ways.
Meanwhile, the sun remains still,
and the individual planets
move in sequence.
The cosmos is unified
under a single order.
Common sense is overturned.
The Church is enraged.
Reason and beauty become one.
That is my research.
I suppose
we could call it...
heliocentrism.
How about that?
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
CHAPTER ONE
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb