ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE TEN
TRUTH
I'm coming in.
Badeni?
I know it's sudden,
but I need this barn for my research.
I don't want to work at the church.
For the time being,
I'll need you to use another--
Huh?
What is that?
Oh, uh...
I've been learning to read and write.
Jolenta taught me.
What?
Unbelievable...
How could Jolenta do such a thing?
Teaching the written word
to someone of your class?
Huh?
You don't get it.
It's a good thing
that most people can't read or write.
Reading and writing are special skills.
To leave words behind
is a heavy responsibility.
It requires certain natural gifts
and a minimum level of education.
If the written word
were available to everyone,
unreliable information
would flood the world.
It would be a dire situation indeed.
Th-That's...
Besides, what use do you have
for reading and writing?
Well, I...
I'm thinking of writing a book.
What?
Of course, I have no intention or means
of making it public.
It's more like a diary.
I won't reveal my name.
Huh?
I sort of want to write about
the work we've done so far.
What?
But of course,
I can't write anything technical.
It would be more like a story.
H-Hold on a second.
There's a lot I want to say.
But first off,
why would you do that?
What?
Why would someone like you,
who could never read or write,
want to write about these past few months
and risk putting someone on our trail?
And why now?
That's, uh...
Never mind.
You won't be able to write much anyway.
And even if you manage to,
I'll burn the pages, so do as you please.
I might lose my mind
if we continue this conversation.
Could you please leave?
Forgive me.
Father Grabowski!
Why do rainbows occur?
They are God's way of congratulating us
for withstanding the rain.
- Wow!
So then, why do rainbows
have so many colors?
Oh, uh... that's...
Well...
Excuse me, Badeni.
Huh? Badeni?!
Oh, sorry.
I haven't been sleeping much.
A-Are you okay?
Yes.
Um, sorry to disturb your rest, but...
Do you know why rainbows
produce so many colors?
The children asked me just now,
but I couldn't answer.
You expect me to tell you for free?
Oh, uh... very well.
I'll arrange for extra ink and paper.
That'll do.
According to Epicurus,
rainbows occur when sunlight
passes through a moist atmosphere.
Furthermore, the colors
are produced, in part or in whole,
by a special bond that occurs
between the light and the atmosphere.
The resulting light is reflected
and absorbed again by the atmosphere,
leading to the final array of colors.
That sums it up.
Thank you very much.
So, how do I explain that to the children?
I have no idea.
Are we done yet?
Badeni,
have you read Epicurus's work?
Yes, I had reason to do so recently.
Of course, I only did it
to refute his pagan ideas,
so don't bother telling me that
his atomic theory is atheistic in nature.
In that case, have you read
Lucretius's work too?
The poet who praised Epicurus.
Well, yes.
Really?
To be honest,
I joined the monastery in part
because I wanted to read his work.
I never got the chance though.
But of course,
my interest stems
from a desire to help the Church.
I see.
Why Lucretius, though?
Because so many learned men quote him.
It's said that Lucretius's poems are
inspiring.
Oh, but since it was written by a pagan,
I'm wary of course.
If you've read his works,
I'd be grateful
if you could share even a portion--
I'm afraid I refuse.
You should know
that I have no interest
in the sharing of knowledge.
In fact, I despise it.
When commoners seek knowledge,
it only leads to tragedy.
Furthermore, an ordinary person
without the proper qualifications
has no need for it.
But that's...
Excuse me then.
I can't take it anymore.
Badeni's attitude is intolerable.
How can a disciple of the Church
be so arrogant?
Ordinary people without qualifications?
He's far too prejudiced.
Every individual has a purpose!
Wait, but if I look at it that way,
Badeni has his purpose too.
I may disapprove,
but I can't be wrathful toward a neighbor.
I have much to learn as a believer too.
Remember!
My role
is to aid the villagers in their faith.
Focus only on that.
That's right.
Why would I need knowledge
of a pagan like Lucretius now?
Why should I want to...
Father Grabowski!
Oh, forgive me. I must have drifted off.
That's only because
you work so hard for us.
That reminds me.
Do you all want to hear
the story of how Badeni
got that scar on his face?
Oh! I've been wondering
about that scar for a while.
Please tell us!
That's what I thought.
Before Badeni took the cloth,
he attended a certain private school.
His close friend also attended,
with whom he performed joint research
and shared information.
So, even Badeni has friends, huh?
But one day,
that friend stole credit
for Badeni's research.
That's not the surprising part though.
When Badeni confronted him,
his friend was enraged
and challenged him to a duel!
You don't mean--
That's right. Badeni is alive.
That means the duel ended
with Badeni killing his close friend.
The scar he has now
is the result of that fight.
How awful!
Where did you hear such a story?
From Badeni himself.
I asked him about the scar,
and he told me.
Wait, you mean a killer
became a clergyman?
If the duel happened
before the candidate joined the clergy,
the Church will overlook it
if they have a logical reason to join.
In either case, it's a frightening story.
Yes.
Please make sure Badeni
keeps to himself, as he does now.
Excuse me.
Huh?
I'm sorry for prying,
but I heard the story about your scar.
That must have been painful.
I suppose. We were close after all.
So, why?
Huh?
Why, after experiencing such tragedy,
do you still engage
in research or scholarship?
Because I don't want to discard
the potential that God provides us.
Thanks to that,
I could even be present
at a moment of historical significance.
Even so,
your uncontrollable curiosity
and unnecessary thirst for knowledge
are without limit.
One day that will become its own purpose
and lead you to immoral behavior.
Isn't the world already full
of immoral behavior?
Grabowski,
what do you think is necessary
to change such a world?
Huh?
Truth.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
Truth, huh?
And that's why it should only be handled
by those who are qualified to do so.
Then again, I'm not interested
in doing things for the world's sake.
Hello there, Father Grabowski!
How rare to see you outside the church.
Well, I thought I'd visit
the library in town.
The library? Are you needed there?
It's nothing like that.
I just thought I'd learn something
outside my duties for once.
What?!
It's closed today, of all days?
But why?
Well,
I'm not sorry I came.
Yes, think of it like that.
Huh?
There are still discrepancies
with the contents of the stone chest.
But why?
Why aren't the orbits perfect circles?
Oczy!
Here's your daily bread.
Oh, thank you!
By the way,
have you heard?
Huh?
Count Piast has gone to heaven.
I see.
We'd better pray for him then.
Yes.
Anyway, it seems
they're restructuring the organization,
so Jolenta's busy too.
I can imagine.
It seems she was destined
to pull away from our research.
Putting that aside, I have a request.
Can you start digging a tunnel tomorrow?
Huh?
One from the barn to the church.
We'll need an escape path too,
just in case.
Oh, uh... right.
I'll get back to work then.
Excuse me!
In return for doing that work,
I also have a request.
Oh?
You're negotiating with me
when I'm in a bad mood
after research has stalled?
That's shrewd of you.
Uh...
Never mind. What is it?
Could you increase my bread rations?
I, uh...
You want more for the beggars, don't you?
Did you think I wouldn't notice?
You've been handing them out in secret.
As I told you before, it's a waste.
It won't bring you closer to heaven.
Well, I won't tell you to stop,
but no bread increases.
Rations are fixed.
It's still wrong.
The calculations contain errors.
They don't match Count Piast's records.
Why?
The theory itself is flawless.
With the Sun at the center,
planetary orbits must be perfect circles
with no retrograde movement.
Wait, even a man like Count Piast
was still human.
The records may be imperfect.
After all, he assumed
that the geocentric model was true.
That bias may have impacted his accuracy.
The problem isn't the theory
but the records?
What is this necklace?
Is it Oczy's?
Even with two centers,
one can draw a circle.
In doing so, the orbit would be...
elliptical?
Thanks to the stone chest,
I know the orbital period of Mars.
If I apply that and draw lines
from the fixed stars to the Sun and Mars,
I could use the point of intersection
to calculate Earth's position.
Based on that, if I pick a date
when Mars was observed from Earth
and compare it to observations
of Mars 1.88 years later,
the orbit of Mars would be...
Yes.
Yes!
Dear Lord... I may have it.
If I continue with this method,
perform precise calculations,
and create a polished treatise...
Huh?
Is this the book that Oczy was working on?
How strange.
He gives charity, despite not being rich,
and he writes, despite not being educated.
I really don't understand peasants.
There's a large man with his hair tied
who gives you bread, right?
Uh... yes.
I promise that he will continue to do so.
But in return,
there's something I want from you.
I don't have anything.
No.
What I want is up here.
Where is that?
Your rations.
Huh? There's more than usual.
I remembered I don't eat much.
Keep working hard on the tunnel.
How rare.
You're usually in the barn at this hour.
What about research?
Oczy, you can have that barn back now.
Huh?
It's done.
What?
The heliocentric theory is complete.
We finally begin work.
Yeah. To tell the truth, I'm nervous.
Well, let's just do our best.
The Bishop has arrived.
Good afternoon, my dear brothers.
As you all know, from this day on,
you will serve as inquisitors.
Before you begin,
there's something I'd like to say.
It concerns the importance
of your position.
Several hundred years ago,
the fall of Western Rome
plunged the world into disorder.
Chaos and violence ruled,
authority was gained and lost,
and there was nothing to unite
a divided humankind.
People of all types
lost what was dear to them.
In the midst of that turmoil,
the one ray of hope
came from us, the Church.
We spread culture and morality
throughout society,
and brought love and salvation
to everyday life.
The Church binds the people together.
You might think that no one could complain
about such wonderful efforts.
But surprisingly, some do.
They are none other
than the pagans and heretics.
Having lost their faith,
they only find meaning in destruction.
They speak misguidedly of freedom,
break down morality and ethics,
abandon salvation and hope,
and pull the people apart.
All of us, together...
must save the heretics.
They are victims
who have been led astray by the Devil.
When their lives end,
their souls will descend to hell.
Nothing could be worse.
Through your work,
I hope you will guide
the heretics in the right direction.
Those of us alive today have never seen
the world in its former state of madness.
But that is exactly why
we cannot let such an age
fall upon us again.
That is our responsibility.
For our families,
the future, and the faithful.
And for the heretics as well.
You are needed.
Through your work,
through your passion,
please save all humankind.
I'm counting on you.
I think I was taking this job too lightly.
Gotta pull it together.
Yeah, me too.
This is no time for petty complaints.
Yeah.
Let's put our hearts and souls into it.
Hey, you two.
Hi there.
I'm Nowak. I'll be training you.
Pleased to meet you.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb