What's the commotion?
Who are you people?
Where are you headed?
We're tinsmiths.
We're escorting our young one
and this female worker
as they begin their pilgrimage.
Here's our authorization.
Why are you armed?
In case of bandits.
I've heard they're dangerous.
Yeah?
Well, I guess it's fine.
Thank you.
If you don't mind, we're in a hurry.
Wait, please!
Do you have any cloth to spare?
I need some to wrap a torch.
Then you may have my mantle.
No, I couldn't waste something that fine!
Isn't there anything lying around inside?
- Excuse me!
- Huh?
You can have this.
Huh? But...
As you can see, it's quite old.
I was thinking of throwing it away.
In that case, I accept.
Forgive the intrusion!
May God bless you.
You saved us back there.
I'm grateful.
It's fine. Forget it.
I'll lose out too if things end here.
Convictions come with a price, right?
Yes.
Conviction can become a curse.
Keep wandering.
Plus...
If we fail now,
Jolenta's inspiration will die too.
Inspiration?
Yes.
You all would probably toss it aside
as unnecessary sympathy.
In that case, I'll preserve it.
As I listen to your plans,
the future I imagine you'll reach
may contain Jolenta's goals
but not her memories.
Not her guilt, her regrets,
or her doubts.
If you all have inherited her plans,
then I will inherit her heart.
Why?
When did you develop
such an affinity for our leader?
I don't know.
But maybe it's because
someone I met has died.
Oh, and... I promised
to send a letter for her.
Oh! We've been waiting for you, Schmidt.
You took so long,
we thought you must be dead.
It seems my time hasn't come yet,
Bolko.
Who's the girl?
A lost child?
Oh, uh, I'm...
She's a collaborator.
I'm Draka. Pleased to meet you.
She burned the book.
Which means she's now the only one
who knows its contents.
What?
And in return for her telling us,
we promised to loan her
the printing press.
What?
Furthermore,
she recently saved us from danger.
That's all there is to know.
Can we trust her?
At the moment, we have no choice.
Well then, have a look at our treasure.
This is...
Yes, it may not look like much,
but don't be fooled.
It's a printing press.
What about the leader?
She's dead.
- Is that so?
- Yes.
It was all for the sake of this mission.
Do you remember
our organization's philosophy?
We're going to make this world
a more open place.
We'll confront the existing order
and expand new horizons
for future generations.
And how do we do that?
Even the most eloquent voice will fade
if it ceases to speak.
Even the firmest pillar
will decay with time.
Everyone dies.
Everything is in flux.
Even so, we know the way.
The way to strengthen our convictions,
visualize our thoughts,
and turn seconds into eternity.
We will carry this moment far away
to some distant future
or to the hands of another.
We know how it can be done.
Our method is impactful.
We have the power to dissolve
the existing order and social classes.
We will make it happen.
Let us now begin our publishing operation!
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE 21
THE TIMES ARE CHANGING
Frei...
These are the manuscript and type.
Good. In that case,
I will build the letterpress.
So, what book title will grace
our first-ever page?
"On the Movements of the Earth."
Right. For that--
Wait a second.
No one knows
that Jolenta is the name
of the Liberation Front's leader, right?
No.
Then it should be safe.
Why don't we put her name
on the cover as publisher?
Yes, that sounds good.
You got it.
This is bad.
Some of the letters have cracked.
It must have been then.
Well, type does break easily.
Damn it!
All the "N"s are cracked.
We have no choice.
We'll have to halt operations for now.
We'll acquire lead in town.
Right.
What about these?
- Huh?
They're made of lead.
What if you melt them?
This should be enough to help, right?
Yes, but...
It's fine.
I'd rather see the printing start.
We owe you one, girl.
Then let's begin.
So this is... movable type.
ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
PUBLISHED BY JOLENTA
Okay! Bring paper!
We'll print as much as we can!
You three find out
if there's any way to get lead in town.
But don't raise suspicion.
Everyone else, help set the type.
- Yes, sir!
Everyone... get to work.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Things are going well.
We should be able to transport them
in a few days, right?
Yes, the technology is impressive.
Once it starts, it's fast.
If this succeeds,
we'll have more options in the future.
The future?
It's my turn to guard the horses.
Right.
This is the final stage.
We're one step closer
to our ultimate goal.
It's all according to plan.
No problems at all.
As I listen to your plans,
the future I imagine you'll reach
may contain Jolenta's goals
but not her memories.
I'll inherit her heart.
No. Everything is as God intended.
Feelings are of no concern.
If I waver now,
I won't be able to achieve my own goals.
That's right. The plan has succeeded.
Captain.
Huh?
I know I'm repeating myself,
but allow me to ask one more time.
This mission
could be called
our most important task, correct?
Yes.
This location
was worth trading
the leader's life to keep secret?
Yes.
If we were to be found here,
it would be a disaster?
Yes.
And finally, the horses we had here
were our only means of transport, correct?
Yes.
Good.
Then my work here is done.
Did you report us?
Yes.
While I was in town.
Strike the final blow.
The knights will be here soon.
You won't even have time
to take the printing press!
My victory is secure.
Why did you betray us?
On whose orders?
Whom do you serve?
No one.
God and justice, perhaps.
All this time, I've hated you people.
I've hated you heretic filth!
You've killed
just as many knights as I have.
You're guilty too.
It was a necessary sacrifice
to pursue my convictions.
I will extinguish you all.
That's been my conviction
since the day I was born!
I have no doubts!
You're awfully sloppy
for someone pursuing their convictions.
Isn't it too early to confess?
As long as the knights haven't arrived,
we can still escape.
You can't be sure we'll be killed.
You don't get it.
This is an act of mercy.
- Mercy?
- Yes.
I'm giving you time.
Time to understand your own shallowness.
Time to experience despair.
And finally, time to repent.
It's not too late for salvation.
As a true believer,
I'll hear your confession.
So say it!
Say that the Church orthodoxy
you've mocked was right all along!
Say it to me!
Now!
You can't see it, can you?
This righteous... cross...
Captain!
Several suspicious carriages
are heading this--
Huh?
Frei has betrayed us.
What?!
And that's the situation.
I hid the molds and the manuscript.
But what do we do with the printing press?
We have no time to think.
Our enemies are closing in,
and we have no horses.
But that's...
Are you suggesting
we abandon the printing press?!
That's the least of our problems.
This place has broad visibility.
They'll spot us wherever we run.
Worst case scenario... we'll all die.
That's correct.
But there's nothing else we can do.
We should all run in separate directions.
Those who are lucky enough
to escape will start over.
Realistically,
that's our only way to survive.
It's our one and only option.
No.
There are two.
If publishing is the goal,
there's one other option.
What's that?
You can all work together
to ensure that I escape.
What do you mean?
I'll explain my plan.
A-Are you out of your mind?!
That will never work!
Do you realize who we're about to fight?!
It's the Church itself!
I know that.
But... rather than the Church,
I'll talk to him personally.
If we steal a horse,
I can get there in a few hours!
It's impossible!
Nothing is impossible!
Especially when it comes
to people's hearts!
I don't believe in God.
You all may reject my stance,
but it enables me to see things you can't.
The times are changing.
No, they have to change.
And I can take advantage of it.
I can convince him!
I assume you understand
what you're asking of us.
It's true that if we work together,
we can ensure that one or two escape.
But in return,
the rest of us will die.
Yes. Of course.
But the book will be published.
Isn't that this organization's goal?
That's why there are two options.
A chance few can escape
or one of your choosing.
I disagree.
Even if we helped you escape,
I doubt you'll convince anyone.
The chances of success are too slim.
That said, even if a few of us
besides you were to get away,
the chances of obtaining
another printing press,
on top of achieving
publication and distribution,
are still very low.
What'll it be, Captain?
I know a good way
to break deadlocks like this.
We'll ask God.
Heads, everyone runs.
Tails, you help me escape.
Here we go.
Wait.
Are you sure
you're okay with this?
Yes.
It's heads.
Everyone runs.
Okay! Hurry up, everybody.
You run.
We'll protect you.
Hear that, everyone?
Captain, is that a suggestion?
It's an order.
Understood.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb