Who are we?
I've no doubt that we are those
who will inherit the coming age.
Having broken free of the prejudices
and discrimination of old,
we will freely, nimbly, and elegantly
plunge into the unknown.
And today, a new comrade
has joined our quest.
His name is Albert.
Welcome!
We're glad to have you!
I've served as his tutor,
and his clear thinking has amazed me.
It's as if a master theoretician
has entered into a young boy's body.
However, what I find even more remarkable
is his intense curiosity.
No other talent
is more important
to the future of academia.
I say that because I am afraid.
Perhaps in the future,
the view that truth is conceived,
rather than discovered,
may become an assumption of sorts.
Written works of the past
and other countries
all describe different histories,
cultures, and faiths.
Information is in short supply now,
but if we connect with those
foreign to us in the days to come,
even truth may one day
be seen as relative.
When that happens,
awe and admiration
for the ideal of universal truth
may fade from human hearts.
As a result, research will become
increasingly specialized.
The grand desire for contact
with knowledge as a whole,
in other words, curiosity itself,
may be despised as frivolous and wasteful.
If that happens,
I can't help but feel sad.
That's why I choose
to believe.
I believe in all of you
and your curiosity.
Here's to your curiosity
and that of our newest member!
Cheers!
- Cheers!
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Oh man, I spoke too long again.
Um, excuse me.
Thank you again.
I don't know what to say,
but I'm very happy
that you invited me here!
Don't be so humble.
We're equals here.
Anyway, I have an errand to attend to,
so I'll take my leave.
But you should enjoy yourself.
They're probably discussing cosmology
at that table over there.
It should interest you.
Cosmology?
You came all the way here,
so it would be a shame if you left early.
Be sure to stay until the end.
Yes, of course!
Well then, see you later.
That's where the secret information
I obtained comes in.
A prominent man named Ibn al-Shatir
adopted the stance of the Maragha scholars
and refined the uniform motion
of Ptolemy's--
- Oh!
- Huh?
Sorry, it's nothing!
Please continue.
Right. Anyway, what Ibn al-Shatir did was...
Oh, no.
I forgot to record my observations today.
What do I do?
If I go home now,
the meeting will be over
by the time I get back.
Then again, this is a special day.
It won't hurt if I skip
my observations just this once.
...there's another way to look at it.
- Huh?
- Sorry, I have to go.
Thank you very much for today!
Huh? Sure.
Come again, okay?
I will. Farewell!
If I'm lucky,
I can borrow Father's horse
and go back right away.
I might make it in time!
I'm back!
Huh?
Oh, my.
Huh? W-What are you...
Oh, uh...
Man, this is a dilemma.
Well, I understand how you feel.
You must be confused.
Even so, I'd like you to stay calm.
If you deal with it rationally,
this too can be understood.
I have faith in you.
Let me say first
that I never intended this to happen.
I wanted to settle things peacefully.
Anyway, I'll start from the beginning.
Recently, I heard a rumor
that your father possessed
certain materials.
These materials deal
with a revolutionary theory
that could change
the shape of the universe.
I've been interested in that theory
for as long as I can remember,
but I had given up hope
of ever tracking it down.
I thought I had finally found
an entry point.
So I proposed sharing the materials
and engaging in joint research.
It wasn't a bad offer, I'd say.
To be honest,
the theory is beyond your father's grasp.
Without my intellect and social position,
its value will be lost.
I would have compensated him fairly,
and we both would have benefited.
But that's when the problem started.
He refused my offer.
Without a second thought.
Instead,
he insisted that the theory
conflicted with the prevailing models
and that it might be suppressed.
"I have a child.
I can't take on anything dangerous."
Those were his words.
He was an awfully fussy man.
With the right political moves,
suppression can easily be avoided.
But he wouldn't listen.
No, it was worse than that.
When I tried to convince him,
he grew angry.
In the end, he said
he would burn the materials.
I have to say,
that left me speechless.
Despite all his talk
of knowledge and learning,
he was a boor
concerned only with self-preservation.
Oh, I guess I shouldn't
speak ill of your father.
I take that back. Sorry.
In any case, he grew hysterical,
and I thought he might
do something drastic.
And so, I pacified him.
In the only way I could.
Your father
kept knowledge to himself
and refused to share.
That is an intolerable sin.
That way of thinking must be eliminated.
Understand?
The important thing here
is that the knowledge
your father inherited
will no longer be lost.
To pursue the beauty of this world,
sacrifices are unavoidable.
Now then, that clears things up, right?
In the end,
just as he finished his speech,
he was captured by the townspeople.
I don't know the rest.
It's ridiculous, right?
It all meant so little.
My father
told me to doubt.
As a result, he trusted no one
and was killed
for not sharing his materials.
My teacher
told me to believe.
As a result,
he had such faith in his convictions
that he didn't question murder.
That's the fate of people
who deal with knowledge.
"Truth" and "learning"
are too big a burden for humans.
That's why university
is a fool's path.
Do you have to choose between them?
Huh?
Doubt and conviction.
Would it hurt to have both?
Yes, it would.
They contradict each other.
St. Thomas Aquinas wrote that knowledge
is both material
and immaterial.
Body and soul.
Reason and faith.
Philosophy and theology.
Doubt and belief.
These contradictions coexist.
Why?
Because we're human.
Human beings are neither God nor beast.
They exist between the two.
But that's exactly why
they can accept contradiction,
ambiguity, and confusion.
In fact, such things provide
a breather from reason.
Listening to you,
it seems that you no longer
feel God's presence.
In other words,
you no longer sense what a miracle it is
that our world exists.
Miracles are chance phenomena
that occur when inevitability rules.
At the same time,
they are also inevitable phenomena
that occur when chance rules.
You felt those things back then.
You knew that everything
in this world is a miracle.
But as you cast aside
experience and memory,
your past and roots,
and finally pain itself,
you also lost the miraculous.
Even though that realm
is where you truly belong.
That's not for you to decide.
Do you know what you should do?
I don't have a clue.
It's simple.
Look up at the sky.
And then, take a deep breath.
My problems aren't that simple.
Of course not.
But even so, they are not insurmountable.
Letters to the Corinthians,
Chapter 10, Verse 13.
"God is faithful;
and he will not let you
be tempted beyond your ability,
but with the temptation
he will also provide the way of escape,
that you may be able to endure it."
Now then,
you showed the courage to speak,
so I will confess my own secret worry.
In my case...
Long ago,
I left a friend for dead.
In the course of his work,
my friend committed a terrible crime.
Something irreversible.
As a result,
he died.
But it was the very severity of his sin
that made it important
to show him the path of salvation.
What was the correct choice
for me at that moment?
I still have no answer.
I don't know if I ever will.
However, one thing is clear.
Before today,
I had turned a blind eye to my past.
But now I was able to express it
in words for the first time.
By doing so, I'll probably suffer
even more from now on.
But at the same time,
I'll believe today was a first step.
The same goes for you.
You told me your worries.
Now you can move forward.
God will accept us.
And God will always offer us a refuge.
But for that to happen,
we must overcome ourselves
and face God with sincerity.
In addition,
we must question in solitude
whether we are worthy of God's acceptance.
But no matter how much
we struggle with that question,
God will remain silent.
That's right.
And that's what enables us
to continue thinking, without end.
I'd like to believe that is happiness.
Finally,
I have one question for you.
To obtain bread, one offers coin.
To obtain rights, one offers taxes.
To obtain wages, one offers labor.
So then,
what must one offer up
to obtain the truth of our world?
What do you think?
Go in search of the answer.
Why?
So you can resume living in this world.
I think going to university
might be one way to find out.
Farewell, and may God bless you.
To pursue the beauty of this world,
sacrifices are unavoidable.
No matter what happens,
I'll never criticize your curiosity.
Teacher,
I want to pursue the beauty of this world.
To do so, sacrifices are unavoidable.
To be honest,
I feel the same way.
But you couldn't reach beauty
with the methods you chose.
I don't know what must be offered up
to know the truth of this world.
But I'm certain
that hiding things like my father
or eliminating others like you
is not how it's done.
We all lack something.
That's why we work together.
The world is too big
of a challenge otherwise.
Humans are social animals.
Teacher,
I too feel thaumazein.
I will continue to affirm that feeling
in ways different from you.
I'll doubt as I move forward
and believe as I turn back.
My pursuit of beauty
and inspiration
will never end.
Oh, you're back.
- That took longer than expected.
- Master!
Please allow me to attend university.
Let's see.
You're our new applicant.
Albert, wasn't it?
Yes.
In that case, sign here.
Albert... Brudzewski?
Yes.
Brudzewo is the name of my hometown.
I use that name for my signature.
I see.
Well, anything will do.
Starting tomorrow,
take whatever classes you like.
What? A letter?
For me?
Yes. It's addressed to Potocki.
Potocki?
I don't know anyone by that name.
Still, this is definitely the address.
Well, that is what it says.
But then... could it be intended
for the previous occupant?
I mean, I've never seen
anything like this.
"Certificate of title."
"In the event that
the following book is published,
you will receive
ten percent of the profits."
It's kind of creepy.
Plus, isn't this a weird name for a book?
"On the Movements of the Earth," it says.
That must be a mistake.
After all, it's the heavens that move.
It's way too suspicious.
They didn't even send
the book in question.
Then again, if it brings me money,
I'm fine with that.
On the Movements of the Earth, huh?
Hmm?
In 1468,
Albert Brudzewski enrolled
at the University of Kraków at age 23.
He would eventually work there
as a teacher for 20 years.
His lectures focused mainly
on mathematics and natural philosophy.
At one point,
he expressed skepticism toward
the traditional geocentric model
but refrained from drawing conclusions.
In 1482,
he wrote a commentary
on the astronomy textbook of the time,
New Theories of the Planets.
It would go on to be widely read
at the university.
In 1491,
one of the students
who learned astronomy from his commentary
was a young man named Copernicus.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
THE END
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb