Father will be home soon.
Okay, my rough notes have been burned.
The revised documents are in here.
Good. It's almost full.
I'm home, Rafal!
He's not here?
Huh? What could he have burned?
Th-This is...
It can't be.
As expected,
proving heliocentrism won't be easy.
The orbits I've calculated
are still far from perfect circles.
At this rate, the geocentric model
is still more accurate.
- Hello there.
- Huh?
- We met the other day.
- Oh!
G-Good afternoon.
I'm sorry about all that.
I've heard you're pretty smart.
You're entering university already?
Oh, uh, yes!
I'll begin studying theology
in the next term.
Oh? How impressive.
I'll do my best to contribute to society.
Well then. Farewell.
- Just a second.
- Huh?
That...
Didn't that necklace
belong to Hubert?
Why are you wearing it?
It's a reminder.
A reminder of my anger at his heresy
and the need to remain vigilant.
Is that so?
Do you know what he was researching?
No, not a thing.
I see.
He contradicted geocentrism,
the proper model of the universe.
I'd just like to confirm.
Will you swear to God
that you weren't involved?
Of course. I swear it.
I believe in the universe
that we are taught.
Thanks for your cooperation.
If you'll excuse me.
That freaked me out!
He can't just appear suddenly like that!
Still,
why do they put so much emphasis on words?
Huh?
It didn't burn?
But why is it on my desk?
Don't tell me Father--
My calculations have been revised.
That paper can have trouble burning.
You should watch
until it's completely burnt.
These revisions...
Did you do them, Father?
I know nothing about any of this.
I've been acting too much
in the open lately.
The lack of materials
had stalled my research.
Maybe I should rest awhile
and resume my research
when I've settled at university.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Rafal!
EPISODE THREE
I... BELIEVE IN HELIOCENTRISM
Is he out?
What have I done?
Why did I revise those calculations?
If...
I were to be caught...
Hi there.
G-Good afternoon.
Sorry for the sudden intrusion.
I'd like to follow up
on a few matters concerning Hubert.
Oh, and could I have some water too?
Huh? Uh, yes.
My, my! That was some commotion.
Hubert was a student of yours, wasn't he?
Even if he was a heretic,
it must be hard on you.
N-No.
I recognize his heresy.
Furthermore,
he was just one of many students
I've had over the years.
I have no special feelings for him.
You have a previous charge
of heresy yourself.
Weren't you also researching
the heliocentric theory?
Th-That was a long time ago.
I've fully recanted.
I've never spoken
with Hubert about research.
I imagine that's true.
It's likely that Hubert looked into
your past research on his own.
And since your recantation,
you've devoted yourself to theology,
taken in orphans, and desperately
tried to improve your reputation.
I'm sure you want to avoid
a second charge of heresy.
Those who betray the faith twice
have the devil in their bones.
For the sake of the heretic too,
we take the strongest measures
to exorcise the evil.
You know what that means, right?
You burn them... alive.
Exactly.
I haven't directly experienced
the suffering they go through,
but there are some who break
their jaws clenching to resist the pain.
How terrifying.
However, the physical pain of the flames
is the least of their worries.
Someone like you will know what I mean.
Their bodies turn to ash.
There is nothing left
to be restored on Judgment Day.
Academics are divided
about what happens next,
but here's what I think.
I think they experience nothingness.
Memories, experiences, consciousness,
the soul, and the afterlife
all turn to nothing.
I sure wouldn't want that fate.
Now then...
Your child is conducting
blasphemous research, isn't he?
What?
I hit the mark, huh?
A heretic that young...
What is the world coming to?
How can you just accuse him?!
Do you have proof?
No.
Not yet anyway.
But you know, Potocki.
If you knew he was
conducting blasphemous research,
and you didn't turn him in,
it would be over for you.
If you know something,
you should tell me soon.
Before I gather the evidence.
Plus, it's only the boy's first offense.
If he recants,
he'll be released immediately.
Turning him in now
would save everyone a lot of pain.
Well,
that's all I have to say.
Sorry to bother you.
You really...
You really won't execute him
for a first offense?
No. Of course not.
Father.
Oh, Rafal.
So you're home.
Is something wrong?
The revisions
to my calculations...
Huh?
- Was it you--
- Rafal.
Do you think you can prove heliocentrism?
Yes.
I see.
Father--
Forgive me. Please go to bed for now.
We'll discuss this further tomorrow.
Please.
Good morning.
I'm sorry, Rafal.
Now then. Shall we depart?
That takes care of the arrangements.
Your torture officially begins tomorrow.
This here is still a prototype.
I call it the Pear of Anguish.
When you wind it,
it opens up like this.
After four turns with this in your mouth,
your cheeks will split,
and you won't speak for a year.
You probably don't know,
but the world is full of tools
that are designed
to inflict pain effectively.
Pain is something no one can escape,
but there are two ways to avoid it.
Recant at your trial tomorrow,
and proclaim you'll never
associate with astronomy again.
Tell us where all your materials
are located and burn them yourself.
Th-That's it?
Yes. Even I prefer not to torture a child.
Oh, and this.
It's yours, right?
Your university admission form.
It's still valid, you know.
You can recommit your life to theology.
The most important choice you make in life
is what to give up.
You're smart, right?
You'll know the right answer.
Until tomorrow.
Let's meet when you're reborn.
Recant and burn my materials.
Well, I guess I can do that.
I've managed to come this far.
This too
will work out somehow.
Recanting is not the end.
Burning my materials is not the end.
Being charged is not the end.
Whether astronomy is prohibited,
or I'm all alone, it's not the end.
It's not
the end.
The end...
Why am I doing this?
How did I end up here?
If I'd never learned about heliocentrism,
I would never have found myself here.
If not for heliocentrism,
I'd still be considered intelligent.
I'd be celebrated by those around me.
My lifestyle would be comfortable,
my future would be promising,
and my path forward full of hope.
The world would still be easy.
Why did I do this?
What does heliocentrism mean to--
Moon... light?
Hasn't this happened before?
Just like back then,
continuing with astronomy isn't rational.
the sky is far away.
Not only that,
the window I have now is even smaller.
But...
But why?
Now, more than then,
I can see the sky
clearer than ever.
Was it always this beautiful?
Does the accused confess
to researching the heliocentric theory
that heavenly bodies
revolve around the Sun, rather than Earth?
Yes, I confess.
Were you aware that this theory
contradicts Church doctrine?
Yes, I was.
The Church seeks from the accused
an official recantation,
as well as the disclosure and destruction
of all related documents.
Understood.
In consideration of the accused's
impressive academic record,
the Church is prepared to permit
university admission
if he agrees to our demands.
Will you accept the admission form?
The important thing
is what to give up.
Choose correctly.
They're only words.
This will all work out.
Now, please recant.
I hereby declare
that I believe in heliocentrism.
Why?
You allow prisoners
to drink such fine wine?
It's a special privilege
on the eve of torture.
I see.
Will you drink with me?
It's a shame to do so alone.
Why did you ruin our deal?
It's simple, really.
I thought not burning my materials
would aid heliocentrism.
There's no use.
Don't underestimate torture.
By tomorrow afternoon,
you'll have told us everything.
Your enemy is a resilient one.
The thing you all oppose isn't me.
Nor is it heretics.
It's part imagination
and part curiosity.
In short, it's truth itself.
Truth itself?
It spreads like an epidemic.
Not even the host can control it.
It's not the sort of harmless thing
that can be tamed by an organization.
So you're saying you'll win?
You think that
this is the right answer for your future?
Of course it's the wrong answer.
But a wrong answer
is not a meaningless one.
By the way,
do you know the effects of poppy seeds?
Poppy seeds?
Well...
It's said they were used
in ancient Athens.
If you mix them with poison,
simply put, they allow you
to die without pain.
I happen
to have added some just now.
Damn it!
- Not your cup.
- Huh?
The one who drank it was me.
Huh?
What?!
Y-You're lying.
You...
You're out of your mind!
You intend to die?
I guess.
Don't give me, "I guess"!
Besides, such a choice
violates our teachings!
How far will you go
to humiliate the Church?
A terrifying fate
awaits you in the afterlife!
No one knows what the afterlife is.
To paraphrase Socrates,
no one has experienced death,
yet everyone assumes
it is the greatest evil.
Or as Epicurus said,
"When we exist, death is not;
and when death exists, we are not."
Or as Seneca said,
"Life is long if you know how to use it."
I agree with all of them.
Those things were said
by heathens from 2,000 years ago!
They had no absolute God or salvation!
What good are their words?!
They inspire me.
In...
Hubert died and disappeared.
But the inspiration
he left me hasn't faded.
I think inspiration
is probably more important than lifespan.
So faced with this choice,
I will let inspiration survive,
even if it costs me my own life.
You're out of your mind.
You're sacrificing your life
for something you don't understand.
Can't you see
how that is madness?
You're right.
But you could also call it "love."
Now then. May I ask to be alone?
Is it time already?
Yes. Bye now.
TEN YEARS LATER
It should be higher up.
Why is this happening to me?
This...
This is it.
Earth?
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb