EPISODE FIVE
EVEN IF I DIE... THIS WORLD WILL CONTINUE
Come on, Damian.
Did you really need me for this?
This heretic was assigned to Peter.
You can't just loan him to me
for transfer duty.
Nowak.
For a long time, I've been wondering
about your poor attitude.
Huh?
Our work is to serve God
by defending the sanctity of faith.
Complacency is inexcusable.
Don't you realize
that you'll be responsible
if something happens?
Um, wait. I didn't mean...
What? Hey!
What's going on?
What is it?
The wagon in front.
I saw the driver jump off, and now...
What the...
It's those watchmen.
They've betrayed us.
Stop here.
H-Hey, is that permitted?
This is an emergency.
One shot should be fine.
Oh, man.
What a crash.
It can't be saved now.
P-Please help me!
Huh?
Wait!
I was being threatened!
You expect me to believe that?
Well...
He's fully focused.
This guy is tough.
I'd probably die fighting him.
That leaves only one option.
I surrender!
I was wrong! Please have mercy!
Huh?
Seriously?
But that's...
What were the rules
for voluntary surrender again?
Let's see.
"Exercise your own judgment"?
That's the biggest pain of all.
Well, you already double-crossed us once.
Would they allow this?
You're of no use to me anyway.
Huh?
What?
Why?
Because history needs you.
Take this.
- Nowak!
- Huh?
Should I bring your crossbow?
No, don't bother.
What? But why?
It's not worth...
Um, I'd only get in trouble
for using more arrows.
Plus, the thing we need to secure
is lying right here.
As a former soldier myself,
I know it all too well.
Those two can't read a word.
They don't have the brains for heresy.
There's no use going after them.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Um...
I won't run, so you can lower your sword.
Oh, right.
I'm sorry I got you mixed up in this.
Even so, I'm not looking for a do-over.
Given another chance,
I'd probably make the same choice.
So my apology is a bit insincere.
I apologize for that too.
Oh, uh... I understand.
This looks like a clearing.
We might be near the middle of the slope.
Let's look around.
Gras!
I-Is this it?
What is... this diagram?
These seem like letters.
There are two.
One is dated recently, and the other
is from ten years ago.
Can I see the recent one?
It might be from the heretic.
Damn it, my eye...
Let's see.
First, let me state
that I did not create
the contents of this stone chest.
I discovered them.
Therefore, I will record
the story of that discovery.
As an astrologer,
I made a daily habit
of observing the heavens.
One day, while seeking
greater elevation and visibility,
I discovered a spot
that was perfect for observation.
Then I noticed something curious.
Carved into each
of the two nearby rock formations
were three stars
with a mark in the center.
It resembled Orion's Belt.
As if corresponding to the middle star,
the space between the rocks
was in line with the middle
of the mountain on the opposite side.
What could possibly be there?
Who had done this and why?
Spurred by curiosity,
I made my way to the mountain.
And finally, I encountered this chest.
"In the end, I never learned
who left the chest behind
or why they had done so."
"But though the contents
of the chest were incomplete,
it was clear to me that they could change
the history and fate of humankind."
"Even if I were to die
because of the contents of this chest,
I can say my life was fortunate
for having discovered them."
"For further details, I ask that
you confirm the materials herein."
"Selfishly, I too
have adjusted multiple calculations."
"That is all."
What does the other letter say?
Huh?
I don't know.
I never learned to read.
Oh, but...
I think I know what the title says.
What's that?
Earth.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
CHAPTER TWO
It's no use.
This bridge is broken too.
We'll have to go around.
From where we are...
I forgot about this thing.
You're throwing it away?
Yes.
It belonged to the heretic, after all.
Still, it's an important clue.
I'll take it.
Now, let's go.
Earth?
Yes. That's what the envelope says.
Hand it to me. I'll read it.
Let's see.
"I offer you the secrets
of the starry sky."
"If any profit should be earned
from this endeavor,
ten percent should be given to Potocki."
"His support has been valuable."
"His address is..."
Well,
this doesn't tell us anything either.
What the heck is in here?
As far as these documents go,
I'd guess they're related to astronomy.
However, I can't read Latin
or understand the figures.
As far as our future is concerned,
because of my actions,
you won't be welcome
in town or at the guild.
But if I may justify myself,
the circumstances we're in
can be turned to our advantage.
Judging by the volume,
these materials weren't made on a whim.
They're something significant.
Show them to the right person,
and the reward could be big.
Plus, we'd get to learn
about the contents.
Where will you find this "right person"?
I actually have someone in mind.
The monk that told me about the planets.
I believe his name was
Badeni.
You want to discuss heresy with a monk?!
He's no ordinary monk.
He was demoted a short time ago.
The reasons were unruly behavior
and contrarian thought.
Perfect, right?
With that settled, let's go.
Is something wrong?
My... head is spinning.
I've come this far,
but now that I have time to think,
I don't see why I should go with you.
Will you decide for me, Gras?
If I should go or not...
Two is safer than one,
so I'd appreciate a companion.
In that case, I'll go with you.
Oczy.
Could you find the North Star for me?
We should orient ourselves.
I'm afraid I injured my eye earlier.
Forgive me, but I can't do that.
Huh?
But with your vision...
I... can't look at the sky.
I, uh...
I'm afraid.
A priest told me something once.
The night sky is beautiful
because we gaze at it
from the lowly Earth.
Since then, when I look at the sky,
the stars appear to me like eyes
looking down on humankind.
I know that sounds strange.
Before that, could you look at the stars?
Y-Yes.
Actually...
I think I enjoyed it.
You've never had the urge
to see the stars again?
No. It's too scary.
But if it was something you enjoyed,
it's a shame to give it up, right?
I guess so...
Then again, it doesn't concern you, Gras.
Of course not.
But I lost my family in the past,
so I know what it's like
to lose the things you love.
Compared to that, my problem is minor.
After all, I'm still alive.
That's not true.
For you, it's a major problem.
Oh, but...
In your case,
I'm sure they were never lost.
Your family is surely in heaven now.
You'll reunite with them there.
Thank you. I believe so too.
However,
what I really lost
was my hope for this world.
Until recently,
I did nothing but curse this world
that stole my family.
But when I thought deeper,
this world was where I met my family too.
And if that's the case,
I don't want to deny
the world that gave them to me.
It may be difficult,
but I want to view
the world positively once more.
This may sound cruel,
but I don't think that's possible.
Heaven is our only hope.
This world is corrupt.
It's that way
because that was God's will.
The great figures in history
have told us that.
Have you...
Have you completely given up on our world?
Yes.
Only loss awaits us here.
We're all going to die anyway
and end up in heaven or hell.
So that should be our bigger concern.
"Heaven is our only hope"?
So then, why did that heretic
risk his life and his place in paradise
to honor our world?
Humans die.
What would be the point
in loving this world
that we will eventually leave?
When we die, all that remains
is a world without us.
How could there be hope in that?
Wait.
Could that be it?
Oh, good. This bridge is standing.
The village is on the other side.
I guess we're safe for now.
- Oczy.
- Yes?
I've made you come with me this far.
So from this point,
I'd like you to choose.
What?
There are two paths you can take.
First, when we reach the village,
you can report what happened
and the chest we found to the Church.
Do that, and maybe
you can return to the village.
You'll get closer to heaven too.
But what will happen to you?
The second option...
Gras!
This is my...
I'll be brief with the second.
What?! This isn't the time!
The second option
is to ignore the first
and place your hope in this world!
What?
And then, someday,
turn your eyes to the stars again.
What are you doing?!
The ivy will tear!
D-Do you want to die?!
What are you doing?!
- I'm passing the torch.
- What?!
At this rate, we'll both die.
That won't do.
That heretic risked his life
because he found someone to pass it on to.
Just as you said,
this world is full of loss.
Furthermore,
we will all die and leave here someday.
But even if I die...
this world will continue.
That means I can pass the torch.
In a world that is full of loss,
that is one way
that hope is born.
Pass it to whom?! To me?!
Don't expect anything from me!
There's no guarantee I'll do it!
That's true.
But you will.
You aren't ready to go to heaven.
Why?!
Because your face tells me
that you still fear death.
This
is my fate.
H-He's dead.
You really are kind, Grabowski.
You always take the time to listen to us.
That's because I enjoy
hearing your stories.
There you go again.
Unlike that subdeacon from before...
What was his name again?
He's nothing like you.
Indeed.
He may have been praised in the city,
but he's got no compassion.
Oh, don't say that.
Huh?
- What?
Excuse me.
You have a visitor, Badeni.
I'm not expecting a visitor.
That may be, but...
Who are you?
What do you want?
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb