EPISODE SIX
MOVE... THE WORLD
We've never met.
What do you want?
Uh, my name is Oczy.
There are some documents
I'd like you to look at.
If I could guide you to them...
You smell of blood.
You're a mercenary, aren't you?
Forgive me, but I'm a clergyman.
Please maintain your distance.
Uh, right. Sorry.
One more thing.
I'd like to confirm something.
Will these documents
dramatically change my life?
If you can't promise me that,
you're not worth my time.
In a certain sense,
they may be life-changing.
Since... they could anger the Church.
Oh? This might be interesting after all.
Go ahead.
I'll judge how the Church will react.
So, what is this about?
Well, you see...
I don't really know.
Huh? You don't know?
Then why show them to me?
That too. I, uh...
I don't know.
I'm simply doing as I was told.
What? Told by whom?
A long time ago,
when you served at the Abbey in town,
do you remember a man
who asked you about heavenly bodies?
God knows.
The Abbey forced us
to converse with townspeople,
but I was always bored to tears.
I don't remember.
I... I see.
I came at his request.
He was a person
who kept records like these.
Observations of Mars, huh?
Interesting. They're fairly thorough.
I guess even some laypeople...
Huh?
Where is the retrograde motion?
The one that occurs every two years.
It's an important phenomenon.
Oh, about that...
He felt betrayed by the retrograde thing
and gave up on stargazing.
What? He felt betrayed?
He didn't know
that planets move in reverse?
In the first place, the word "planet"
comes from planetes,
the Greek word for "wanderer."
Of course their paths wander.
Someone who knew so little
took these detailed notes?
For what purpose?
I don't know.
Forget it.
I can't spare my time
on something so indefinite.
Go home.
Uh... right.
I got my hopes up for nothing.
Why must I be here
in a place like this?
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Badeni, do you remember
the conditions
for admission to this abbey?
Only those recommended
by three or more
elite universities may enter.
That's right.
Everyone here has been chosen
to do God's work.
I say this with that in mind.
Your work is overwhelming.
Where others work in teams of ten,
you have solved
all these problems on your own.
Yes, Father Abbot.
Amazing.
However,
you must also understand
what this means.
How many times must I say this?
You must not study
more than is expected of you.
You must observe the rules.
Keep in step with the others!
It's futile to cooperate
with people of lesser ability.
Speaking out of turn
is also subject to punishment.
One lashing.
Do it yourself.
Good.
Hey!
I never asked for that much.
May I speak now?
Badeni, how long
do you intend to keep this up?
For as long as punishment
earns me the freedom to study.
You really are a fool.
It's true that you are
our most learned monk,
but you are utterly lacking in prudence.
We cannot afford to be prudent,
Father Abbot.
What?
With such a soft stance,
you'll be swallowed by the times.
If you rely on prudence alone,
you'll never grasp it.
Grasp it?
Grasp what?
What I've been waiting for.
The moment I become special.
My moment of greatness.
The moment I change history!
With such an arrogant attitude,
you'll never be special.
Save that passion for studying theology.
What possible use could you have
for algebra or geometry?
I will use them to solve
God's greatest riddle.
All answers are in the holy scripture.
Then answer me this.
Why do stars
reverse the path of their orbit?
God created two worlds.
This imperfect land below the moon's plane
is subject to cycles
of creation and destruction,
as well as disorderly movement.
Yet the heavens
above the moon's plane are eternal
with no beginning or end.
They should move forever
in a perfect circle.
That I would understand.
But the reality is different.
Within the heavens God created,
circles devolve into peculiar rings
with retrograde movements.
Humankind must confront
the nature of that riddle.
Otherwise,
it means that God's design was flawed.
That cannot be.
And that means
there must be a reason
that humankind has yet to discover!
There is no reason!
It is simply as God ordained.
Humankind will never learn
more about the heavens
than what we know now.
Heaven and Earth are in different classes!
Can a pauper know the mind of a noble?
It would be a freak occurrence at best.
You are capable of such things though.
Huh?
By looking
within the secure vault of our library,
where you keep the forbidden writings
of heretics and infidels.
Don't speak about that.
I am worthy of knowing!
God has given me this talent.
Why must it be restricted by mere humans?
Because curiosity is a sin!
There are many passages
in the holy scripture which tell us that.
Your lust for knowledge is too strong!
Do not think of reading
the forbidden writings, even by mistake.
You won't get off with just a lashing.
What will you do?
I will burn your eyes.
Furthermore, for the time being,
you are forbidden
from theoretical research.
What?
You are still lacking.
Not in knowledge, but in maturity.
That's an unreasonable punishment!
May God bless you.
Damn it.
Anyone could do this.
Why must it be me?
I've acquired all there is to gain here.
Should I give up the cloth
and go to university?
How careless of him.
And the Abbot calls me imprudent?
What's that book cover?
This inscription on the edge...
I knew it! Forbidden writings!
And they're about the cosmos.
Did our conversation spur his curiosity?
You're just as lustful
for knowledge as me.
What are you doing in my room?
You! Don't tell me that's--
Wait.
I haven't witnessed you read it yet.
You still have a choice.
Put the book down and leave!
I will not have our abbey
produce a blinded monk!
Especially not under my watch.
If you open that book,
you will be pinned down in an instant.
There will be no time to read.
It's futile!
You're right.
I can only open it for an instant.
Even so,
I've been waiting for this.
Waiting for such a special instant!
How unfortunate.
"Measurements indicate
that the Sun must be 109 times
larger than Earth. As such--"
No!
Actions like this will destroy
the one true church!
The Pope will be secularized
while the abbeys succumb to dogma!
The Church is getting rich
selling indulgences!
How can you offer hope
to the lost souls like this?
At this rate, opposing sects
will bring the Church crashing down!
If that happens,
you'll take me down with you!
You are hereby demoted.
You'll spend the rest of your life
somewhere far from academia.
Don't think about secular life either.
The Abbey has the power
to forbid any university
from accepting you.
But before that, I'll burn those eyes.
If you're lucky, you won't go blind.
I hope at least one of them survives.
Now then. May God bless you.
Wait!
I'll have a look.
However, I'll need you
to continue those observations.
That's my condition.
M-Me?
Start by observing Mars tonight.
I happen to need it for my own research.
The method of observation
should be described in that diary.
I'm agreeing to help
a suspicious peasant like you.
This is the least you can do.
B-But I...
I can't look at the sky.
Forgive me,
but I have no time for jokes.
Farewell.
It's no use. I can't do it.
Why do I have to do it in the first place?
No, there's no reason I should have to.
That's right.
I should discard these
and start a new life in town.
I can't go back to where I was,
but I can wander until I find
a new place to start over.
I'll be reduced to bottom rank,
but that's no different from now.
After all, suffering
is unavoidable in this world.
If I can endure this, then when I die,
heaven will be waiting!
That's right. Heaven!
Huh?
On the other hand,
those two were the only people I ever met
who valued this world more than heaven.
Surely they went to hell.
I can't listen to people like them.
But then,
for as long as I've lived,
those two were the only ones...
At the moment of death,
no one seemed as satisfied as them.
Why?
They knew they were going to hell.
No! Even if I look, it changes nothing.
Don't expect anything!
Despair can be turned into hope.
Place your hope in this world!
I can't.
But...
Yes... Not bad for your first time.
Now then.
Show me the way to the documents.
Is it something
that will change your life?
No, that's not it.
This
will change the universe.
Orb.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Huh?
It will change
the universe?
What?!
A-Are you okay?!
I'm fine.
I merely vomited
years of pitiful common sense
and preconceptions.
This is amazing.
I knew God made no mistakes.
Even more incredible,
our Lord made a cosmos
that humans can understand.
The Church could definitely be a problem,
but if I find the right interpretation,
publishing isn't out of the question.
What in the world does it say?
Well,
I'll summarize.
It revises and fills the gap between
Aristotle's concentric sphere theory
and Ptolemy's eccentric circles.
In addition, it disputes
the lack of equilibrium
between the cosmos
and its individual points,
as well as the divergent calculations
currently central to all theories.
All those issues can be traced
to the substantial number
of unpredictable movements
among the heavenly bodies.
However, it explains those problems
with a simple theory of motion.
Huh?
Well, to summarize even further...
The Earth is moving.
It's not moving at all.
Right?
But for a mere mistake,
the ideas written here
are far too rational.
Let's try an experiment.
Use that diary to draw
the orbit of Mars over the past two years.
Um...
EARTH, SUN, MARS
Like this?
Yeah. That'll do.
This is the greatest riddle
of the heavens.
Retrograde planetary motion.
Humankind has given up
on finding an explanation for this
and has focused instead
on calculation methods.
As a result,
theories have grown more complex,
employing more and more postulates.
It's all because the planets
don't stick to forward motion.
But in fact, that was wrong.
The planets were moving forward,
even while they moved backward.
Huh? Isn't that impossible?
Yes, it is.
That is, if the Earth is still.
But if the Earth moves,
it's possible.
What are you doing?
I'm mimicking the cosmos.
Walk around this branch,
along the circle closer
to the center, and pass me.
Huh?
Now!
Did something happen?
Yeah.
In that brief instant,
I found the secret to overturning
1,000 years of Ptolemaic theory.
Don't you get it?
As I was Mars,
and you were the Earth,
what did your eyes see?
Huh?
In the beginning,
while I was in front of you,
I appeared to be
moving forward as I circled.
But our difference in speed
closed the gap.
From your perspective,
my velocity seemed to slow
until we were side by side,
and then you passed me.
From your perspective as the Earth,
Mars appeared to move backward.
But once you completely passed me,
Mars seemed to move forward once again.
If there really is no retrograde motion,
and it only appears that way
because we see things
from Earth as bystanders,
planetary motion would look like this.
You can tell which is simpler, right?
Yes.
Do you understand what this means?
That stone chest
is calling out to humanity.
The heavens are sublime, solemn,
sacred, and sweeping.
But they are also
in harmony with the Earth.
The heavens and Earth in harmony?
Are you saying the heavens
are as corrupt as our world?
Or perhaps,
the world we live in
is not the ugly bottom of the universe.
Instead,
it has always been part
of that beauty up there.
In my case, that's what I believe.
B-But that's...
Heaven and Earth
are one?
Could it be?
Tonight's sky somehow...
Do you feel God's grace?
After all, this sky
is offering me a great reward.
Um, that may be...
But in a simpler way...
Huh?
Something about it
seems more beautiful than ever.
There's only one way
to make that "something" absolute.
Move... the world.
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb