Another rough day ahead.
We're sure to be yelled at again.
Huh?
Hey!
You're not permitted, Jolenta.
Yes, I know.
You do, huh?
God, please don't let me be caught.
Don't let me be caught.
Why am I doing this?
I still have time to turn back and yet...
Better not get my gloves dirty.
I don't feel lucky today.
I'm gonna get caught.
My luck has run out.
I just know it.
God has abandoned me for sure.
Oh, Count Piast.
Good morning, sir.
I made it in time!
Skip the pleasantries!
You've wasted enough of my remaining years
with your tedious treatise!
F-Forgive me, my lord.
Well then,
now that Count Piast is here,
we can discuss...
What? The Arabian heretics
have revised ancient Greek astronomy?
I could never hear this anywhere else!
Dear God,
I am lucky indeed.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
EPISODE SEVEN
MATTERS OF THE TRUTH
He was as severe as ever today.
Yeah.
Welcome back!
Huh?
I really do envy you.
You got to rest this whole time.
In that case,
please consider my request
to take part in the discussions.
The answer is no.
We don't know yet
if you are truly suited to this work.
After all,
there is an obvious difference
between you and us.
That's...
Oh, Jolenta.
There you are.
Kolbe!
Hi.
Hello. You must be exhausted.
You have it rough too, Kolbe.
With Jolenta as your assistant and all.
Yes, you said it.
Making use of a capable assistant
can be a real dilemma.
Huh?
What?
I'll tell you as many times as it takes.
Throughout your life,
you may meet people
who completely reject you
for illegitimate reasons.
Those moments
may feel heartbreaking.
But you must believe in yourself
and move forward.
There are times you can't back down.
I'll do my best to support you.
R-Right.
Anyway,
how's that new treatise coming along?
I completed my first draft.
Really?
This is it.
Let's see...
I put everything I know into it.
Fascinating.
Huh?
To write this well at your age is amazing!
R-Really?
That settles it.
I'll submit this to Count Piast.
To Count Piast?
Yes.
I'll need more time to read it,
so take some time off.
In fact,
why don't you visit your family?
My family? Why?
If this is well-received,
you'll be transferred
from the library to the observatory.
Things will get busy.
Go home while you have the chance.
Uh, right!
Yes!
Point one.
The Sun is at the center of the planets.
Two, orbits are perfect circles.
Three, the planets all move
at a set speed.
In summary, these are the arguments
presented in the documents
and the original ideas therein.
Is it true?
- No, it's merely on the threshold.
- What?
Whoever wrote these had a brilliant mind.
The three ideas I listed
are already quite an accomplishment.
So then--
Even so, I'll be blunt.
The documents aren't nearly ready
to be made public.
They've overlooked something.
At this rate,
the ideas will be easy to refute.
Throughout the documents,
their careful word choice
is outweighed by something at their core.
An almost juvenile naïveté.
How mysterious.
Whoever continues this work
must combine a careful intellect
with bold convictions.
It will take a man of true greatness.
Do you know anyone like that?
Of course. It's me.
With that said,
I accept the task.
Accept?
Isn't that what you came to ask me?
Was that it?
I guess it was.
Fair enough.
Before we proceed,
I'd like you to agree to three conditions.
First,
no successors.
If I can't prove the theory before I die,
you must burn all materials
with my involvement.
What's important
is that I be the one
who finishes and releases it.
I refuse to be a stepping stone
for someone else.
Understood.
Second, you will participate
as an observation assistant.
In return, our church will provide you
with food and lodging.
Do you mean it? Thank you very much.
Now for the final condition.
If all goes well and we profit from this,
we'll split it nine to one.
I get the nine, of course.
That won't do.
We can only receive 90 percent.
What?
Well, it's written here.
We're supposed to give
ten percent of the profits to someone.
Huh?
"If any profit should be earned,
ten percent should be given to Potocki."
A co-researcher?
So we can only receive 90 percent...
It's gone now.
With that settled,
let's return to the village.
Uh, right.
Excuse me!
Can't we honor the request?
What? Why should we?
It no longer exists.
Yes, but I'll remember it was there.
What's more, whoever wrote that letter
probably put their trust
in the person who would open the chest.
If we ignore the will
of someone who is gone,
I have a feeling
we'll lose something important.
Like what?
History, maybe?
What?
I have no interest in history
other than the holy scripture.
If you're so eager to pay them,
give them your ten percent.
Oh, right.
Um, one last thing.
As a clergyman,
do you think involvement with this
puts us at the entrance to hell?
Well, we're at an entrance all right.
But it's to the heavens.
It's nice to have
family time after so long.
It's been comforting for me too.
You've been busy traveling, Father?
Here and there.
I suppose you have to go back
to your workplace soon.
Yes, I have work to do.
Is that work causing you any concern?
Huh?
It's written on your face.
To be honest, there's a gap
between me and the others.
You can't keep up?
No, it's bigger than that.
They won't let me
conduct research in the first place.
All I ever do is busywork in the library.
I want to work in the astronomy wing.
Isn't the work you have now enough?
It's impressive that you work at all.
Even so, I passed the same exam
as everyone else.
So why am I treated differently?
It is what it is.
You're still 14 years old.
You're also the only woman
who works there.
A talented woman at that.
Do you realize
how much that worries people?
Yes, but... that has nothing to do
with academic research.
Listen, Jolenta.
There's only one thing
for you to do at your workplace.
Nothing.
Don't stand out.
Don't strive for glory.
If you spend your days in solemn modesty,
you'll join your family in heaven one day.
But you gave me these gloves
so that I could study even in winter.
I've been a scholar at heart ever since.
For God and matters of the truth,
I don't want to retreat.
Not from my talent, progress, or life.
There are times you can't back down.
I understand.
You're an independent woman now.
My parental concern got the best of me.
I'm sorry.
Father!
I'm rooting for you.
Thank you very much!
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
I beg you.
- I beg you.
What are you doing? Let's go.
Yes, sir!
- Charity is meaningless.
- What?
To think that giving alms to the poor
will lead you to heaven
is a ridiculous belief.
They're the biggest sinners of all.
I've never heard
a clergyman talk that way.
It's the fate that God assigned them.
Besides, we're here
to meet with their opposites.
People of means.
If we only have the records in that chest,
we'll never reach a better conclusion.
We need someone
with the means to provide more.
Do you have connections?
No.
They will come to us.
Here we are.
Idle nobles and the wealthy
post and solve problems here
as an intellectual game.
The more difficult
the problem, the better.
Then you mean...
I devised this highly advanced problem.
It'll take astronomical records
and keen intellect to solve.
We'll split up and post these
on prominent bulletin boards.
Then we'll wait for someone to answer.
Will someone really come?
That depends on luck.
Let's meet up at sundown.
If my treatise is praised,
I'll move to the observatory.
Oh, you're back?
Kolbe!
Hi!
Was my treatise--
About that.
Believe it or not, Count Piast praised it!
He said it was fresh thinking.
This is a great honor.
Your talent has blossomed!
- I, um...
- Huh?
I'm truly grateful.
No, don't thank me.
I submitted it in my name after all.
But it's still your work.
Yes, but you're always so supportive...
- What?
- Huh?
In your name?
As I said,
I submitted it in my name,
but you can be proud that you wrote it.
- What?
- Huh?
You submitted my treatise in your name?
Yes, of course I did.
What do you mean "of course"?
Well, you know.
Who would read a woman's treatise?
But that's...
Huh?
Don't tell me you thought
it would be in your name.
Oh, dear. This is a dilemma.
You're far too naïve.
A treatise by a woman
would be incredibly dangerous.
Any inappropriate content
would bring dire consequences.
You could be accused of witchcraft
or executed as a heretic.
But don't worry.
I won't let that happen.
You have great talent.
So, you'll write, and I'll publish.
If I earn enough praise,
I can safely bring you to the observatory.
Stick with me,
and I'll point you in the right direction.
I'll teach you
how to live smart in this world.
But in that world,
my name...
It won't remain.
Give up on that. It's the way things are.
Your name may not remain,
but at least you can publish
your thoughts, right?
Your naïveté worries me.
If you attract the wrong attention,
your life could end in a flash.
Anyway, I'll be waiting for your next one.
Farewell.
Wait!
Count Piast!
You honor us with your presence.
Hey, you.
What?
Did I hear you say
that you wrote that treatise?
My lord, that's uh--
I want her to answer.
Did you?
Th-That's...
I, uh...
A treatise by a woman
would be incredibly dangerous.
But there are times I can't back down.
Do nothing. Don't stand out.
If I back down...
Your life could end in a flash.
Who would read a woman's treatise?
It...
It wasn't me.
I see.
I knew you were smart.
I... was tricked.
Everything he said was a lie.
Kolbe is a wicked man.
If only... that were true.
Things would be much easier.
But it's not so.
He's a good man.
He really is looking out for me.
This must be
the best I can hope for.
This is my reality.
No, think clearly.
It's enough to have
a safe space for research.
My name isn't important.
I've been childish.
If this is how the world is,
it's important to live smart.
On to the next treatise!
What should I write next?
Next...
Why am I crying?
Tears aren't necessary!
If I cry, it's like I've lost!
If I cry, it's like there's a problem!
I just have to move on.
That's all I can do now.
I'd better search for new subject matter.
"Dear reader,
we have a need for theoretical astronomy."
"Please post your response."
What is this?
Oh, I see.
The problem is pretty advanced
for a bulletin board posting.
But wait.
Without astronomical records,
this can't be answered.
Kolbe!
He's not here.
If I act now, I can examine his records!
Here we go.
These are records of Jupiter. How cool.
Everyone else has free access
to all these records.
Wait, right now,
I think I'm doing something bad.
No, it's definitely bad. Unthinkable!
But this might help me
write a new treatise.
That could help Kolbe earn more praise.
Then again, if someone
spots me in here, I'm finished.
Even Kolbe would abandon me.
Yeah.
This is wrong.
It's wrong. I can't do it.
But I don't care if it's wrong.
I want to know the answer!
Forget it. Answer first, think later.
I've finished posting.
Good.
What is it?
There's someone standing
in front of your problem.
Could someone be posting a reply?
What? Already?
We only posted it this morning.
I answered it.
It should be okay, right?
I used a man's name.
But if someone were to see me...
If it's causing me this much anxiety,
I should have thought before I acted.
Keep this up, and I'll be caught one day.
I'd better go before someone sees me.
Excuse me!
Subtitle translation by: Brad Plumb